<title>AJAX</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/ajax.jpg</img>
<date>2/20/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">AJAX is part of the Web 2.0, a structural change in the Internet. With new technologies, companies, and investing, Web 2.0 seeks to expand the web by providing a better, faster, prettier, more efficient, more interactive, and more dynamic internet. AJAX one of the technologies in this web revitalization. Though fairly new, most developers already know the basics of AJAX, contributing to its growing popularity.</p>
<p class="body">AJAX stands for Asynchronous (or Advanced) Javascript And XML. It is a collection of technologies grouped together to make a web platform. With AJAX, data can be accessed from the server by clicking on various items in the web page. This sounds like standard HTML, but with one difference. This data is received, displayed, and updated on the very same page the user is viewing. This enables the browser to work like a platform (such as the Windows operating system), a more seamless experience for the user.</p>
<p class="body">AJAX consists of a few elements:</p>
<ul class="body">
<li>
<b>XHTML</b> and <b>CSS</b> - Extensible HTML is the successor to standard HTML, with a stricter structure. Cascading Style Sheets allow a single "style" to be defined in a document and applied to multiple web pages. Together, these two are the backbone of the web.</li>
<li><b>DOM</b> - Document Object Model is a standard created by the World Wide Web Consortium. Basically, page elements (HTML and XML) can be modified using scripting languages, such as Javascript. What this does is create a more interactive experience for the user.</li>
<li><b>XMLHttpRequest</b> Object - This object allows data to be transferred from the server to the web page asynchronously, or whenever the user desires. The communication isn't always constant, so it saves bandwidth and processor time.</li>
<li><b>XML</b> - Data is transferred in the Extensible Markup Language format, a format that even Microsoft is embracing. Although other formats work, such as HTML, XML is preferred.</li>
</ul>
<p class="body">If you've never heard of AJAX, don't worry. It's been around, but most common people wouldn't find any reason to research it. Companies have a specific interest in it, however, and these companies include Amazon and Yahoo, huge internet powerhouses. Google is one user of AJAX, putting the technology to work in Gmail and Google Maps. Google Maps is an interesting example to use, since it very clearly displays the interactivity that AJAX allows. The main map screen can be moved around, with data being pulled and displayed as fast as the server can send.  The data comes in square image blocks that are accessed when required. This web application is similar to Google Earth, but requires far less disk space.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/ajax/gmaps.jpg','800','603')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/ajax/gmaps_sm.jpg" alt="A view of the University" border="0"></a><br><i>A view of the University</i></p>
<p class="body">Likewise, Microsoft uses similar technology in the Live experience. With Live Mail, the user is presented with an interface reminiscent of Outlook. There's a preview window for emails, which are listed nearby. Clicking delete will automatically change to the next email, while the main page stays the same. Clicking the back button won't bring you to the last email, but it will take you back to the logon screen, an example of how AJAX "breaks" the back behavior.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/ajax/livemail.jpg','800','603')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/ajax/livemail_sm.jpg" alt="The new Live Mail beta." border="0"></a><br><i>The new Live Mail beta</i></p>
<p class="body">Other companies using AJAX include Digg.com. This website (similar to Slashdot, but with a more open atmosphere) uses AJAX to power at least the voting buttons and the reporting tools. There's a lot of coding involved on Digg, with just over 255kb of code required to open the front page. The entire site uses a lot of Javascript and CSS, both elements of AJAX.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/ajax/digg.jpg','800','603')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/ajax/digg_sm.jpg" alt="A screenshot of Digg.com" border="0"></a><br><i>A screenshot of Digg.com</i></p>
<p class="body">AJAX is a definite improvement over web pages with messy HTML and Javascript inserted every which way. However, there are problems with AJAX. Granted, most of them are due to poor design. One of the most common complaints is that the Back button in the browser won't work. Because the Javascript in the page can refresh individual elements, some sites will use one page to display a lot of information. Clicking back will just navigate away from all of the information, when the user really wants to just go back to what he was reading. Going along with this, information won't have a specific URL, forcing users to navigate from a main page. Permanent links are helpful when bookmarking or passing on links, and the lack of them can be very annoying.</p>
<p class="body">AJAX can be slow. The abilities of Javascript make it very attractive, but too much of it really slows things down. In the Digg example, 17 different Javascript files are loaded, for a total of about 240kb. On a 56k modem, that would be about 45 seconds to load everything. That also doesn't include the effect it has on the browser, and the overall system powering the browser. There's only so much a computer can take.</p>
<p class="body">Some people disable Javascript on their computers for security reasons. Javascript can generate annoying popups or flashy ads, as well, and some people absolutely refuse to use it. Since AJAX heavily uses Javascript, these actions effectively break the page. The only solutions are to re-enable Javascript, or not view the content.</p>
<p class="body">One of my largest complains would be that the page doesn't tell me when AJAX is doing something. In Live Mail, a box will come up saying that an action is in progress. On some websites, there is no such thing. Users like me will be very impatient and likely skip that action or spam clicks on the buttons. And sometimes, individual checkboxes will generate an action. What if I want to click on multiple checkboxes? I'd have to wait for every single checkbox to load its actions, and then click the next one. It's not usually a problem, but if the server is slow, it would mean I'm sitting there waiting for something I could have done in one action.</p>
<p class="body">As I said, most of these issues come about as a result of poor design. Not everything can be corrected, but in general they aren't an issue. AJAX doesn't appear to bring much, since Javascript, CSS, and XML were already there before AJAX came about. With a flood of new web standards, AJAX, being a few years old, isn't that exciting. However, AJAX is part of the web, and will likely be a part of it for a lengthy bit of time.</p>
<p class="citetext">References:<br>
<a href="http://sourcelabs.com/ajb/archives/2005/05/ajax_mistakes.html" target="_blank">Alex Bosworth's Weblog</a><br>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX" target="_blank">Wikipedia</a><br>
<a href="http://www.ajaxmatters.com/r/welcome" target="_blank">AJAX Matters</a><br>
<a href="http://project-2501.net/?view=document&id=525" target="_blank">Digg Code Use</a><br>
<a href="http://www.theajaxexperience.com/" target="_blank">AJAX Conference, modified image credit</a></p>
</body>
