<title>AMDELL</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/amddell.jpg</img>
<date>3/4/2006</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body><p class="body">We've all heard the hubbub about DELL and AMD. One week DELL says they're considering offering AMD products, the next week they're not. DELL does offer processors through its website, but not as a part of any DELL computers, and they're not advertising that fact either. To be truthful, this entire DELL/AMD love affair will probably never happen. It's all a bunch of speculation that people like to use to manipulate stock prices. Why won't it happen? Here's why.</p>
<p class="body">AMD doesn't need DELL. Hector Ruiz said recently that they'd be growing, with or without DELL. I'm willing to expand on that and say it would be a huge mistake to let DELL in right now. The reason is that AMD doesn't have the resources to supply all these processors. With the popularity of Opterons and the AthlonX2s, AMD is running pretty close to capacity, if not there already. If DELL started selling AMD chips, AMD would run into supply shortages very soon, upsetting their largest purchasers. They can't afford to do that, not with Intel still outselling them three to one. With AMD opening new fabs, we'll see what happens, but I'm willing to bet that DELL won't seriously offer AMD chips until they can get a guaranteed supply of them. And they're going to want discounts, at least enough to make up for the loss of Intel discounts. AMD doesn't have the cash to do that yet, so for now, AMD won't provide much to DELL.</p>
<p class="body">DELL doesn't need AMD. Every time you think of DELL, you think of Intel, and every time you think of Intel, DELL has to come up sometime. The mindshare of these two companies are incredible, and they are deeply linked. DELL has no reason, yet, to upset Intel and their marketing power by switching to AMD. Since they are pretty much the number one PC builder in America, they're not concerned about adding complexity to their lineup, nor do they want to give up on the huge discounts. Intel doesn't mind giving out these discounts, either. Brand name recognition and the associated power is a big factor. For example, if all my friends are using Intel, I'm probably going to be using Intel too. People buy a Toyota Matrix instead of a Pontiac Vibe (the same exact car) for this reason, because they believe in brand names. Intel's processes are also far more advanced, even if the chips are not. Because of this, I'm willing to bet that it costs Intel much less to produce its chips than it does for AMD. Proof of that is in this: Intel is producing 65-nm chips while AMD is still stuck at 90-nm.  Even with larger die sizes, they have many more fabs and larger wafers to help spread the costs. And Intel's boards are validated, meaning the setup is solid. With AMD, they rely on third party chipsets to provide stability and performance, and let's just say that nForce isn't as bug free as Intel. Sure, many businesses will go AMD, but with Intel, the computers are guaranteed to work. Also, if DELL suddenly started selling AMD, they'd be killing one line of workstations by promoting another, since there are definite differences between AMD (lower TDP and more efficiency) and Intel (validation). So no, DELL isn't about to go and lose discounts, add complexity, and compete with itself.</p>
<p class="body">Could DELL shift manufacturing to produce AMD based computers? Sure. I believe that they have prototypes waiting until the time is right to unveil AMD. It wouldn't cost that much more, since DELL's strengths come from supply chain economics and sheer marketing power. Will they ever shift to produce AMD computers? I highly doubt it will happen soon, if at all. It would probably happen when Intel definitively loses the processor race, but that won't happen in the next decade.</p>
</body>
