<title>Antec Notebook Cooler</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/antec_cooler.jpg</img>
<date>2/18/2007</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">The greatest enemy to all computer electronics is heat, after messy babies and hairy kittens.  Excessive heat leads to hardware failures in all computers, requiring bulky heatsinks and loud fans to remove this heat.  Notebooks don’t have this option, however.  The small, compact form of a notebook requires heatsinks to be tiny affairs and notebook fans to be miniscule in comparison to their desktop cousins.  The solution, then, is to add an external cooler.  Antec makes such a cooler, and today we will be reviewing it.  Antec’s cooler is built large, large enough for a 17” notebook.  The curvy X shape is large and bulky, but provides a stable base for any laptop.  The bottom of the cooler contains a cord compartment to stow the removable USB cable.  The USB cable is the power source for this cooler and includes a passthrough connection, something which is rather clever.  Antec warns that there will be diminished power flowing through the passthrough, which is to be expected.  Overall, the cooler is a simple affair: 2 fans draw air from the base of the laptop and force it out the sides of the cooler.  A switch toggles between the high and low speeds.  A blue LED lights the USB connector area.  How well does it work?  To monitor heat, the program “Notebook Hardware Control” is being used to pull information on the CPU and HD.  Testing was done with a Dell Inspiron 700M laptop with a Pentium M 725 with Speedstep enabled.  The notebook cooler was set to low speed.  Ambient temperatures are roughly 70 degrees F according to the thermostat, standard room temperature.  At full load, the processor drops a mediocre 5 degrees, maxing at 65-67 degrees C instead of up to 73 degrees.  The HD stays a cool 32 degrees compared to the original 45 degrees.  At idle, the processor was at a mere 35-40 degrees C instead of the standard 42-45 degrees C.  The reason I did not test the high speed of the fan was because of the incredible noise level.  The two centrifugal fans are quite noticeable even at low speed, compared to a near-silent laptop.  The sound is comparable to a standard desktop, but the fans are closer and are thus louder.  The quiet hum does not annoy as much as the whine of most fans, however.  At high speed, the noise level is unbearable, audible even over the loud music in noise isolating earbuds.  If you were to ask me if this was a product worth buying, I would have to say yes.  It does everything it advertises and is fairly cheap, at under $20.  Even with fans off, it provides a notebook desk, of sorts, and prevents users from blocking the fans with clothing and bedding.  The noise level is comparable to a standard desktop, so sensitive ears beware.  Overall, it’s a good product, but it could be more silent.
</p>
<p class="body">Images</p>
<p class="body" align="center">
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-15-52_0030.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-15-52_0030.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-17-17_0031.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-17-17_0031.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-18-25_0033.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-18-25_0033.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-18-34_0034.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-18-34_0034.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-22-27_0035.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-22-27_0035.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-22-59_0038.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-22-59_0038.jpg" border="0"></a>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/2006-11-2407-23-06_0039.jpg','800','600')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/antec_cooler/th_2006-11-2407-23-06_0039.jpg" border="0"></a>
</p>
</body>
