<title>AMD Athlon 64, P4 Killer?</title>
<author>Brad Glinka</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/amd64.jpg</img>
<date>10/28/2003</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Well as fall comes upon us again, the two chipmakers are at it again. AMD announces the release of the Athlon 64 and 64fx processors as P4 killers. And of course Intel comes back with the P4ee, but that’s for another day. Yes the new Athlon is the only current 64 bit chip made for the desktop, and yes there are a lot of questions still going unanswered.  But this article should give some insight to the benefits of the new Athlon, and some downfalls.</p>
<p class="body">So another new processor is out, what’s new with this one? Several things that open up unpredicted results, such as an integrated memory controller, 1 meg of L2 cache, and for the first time for an AMD processor, the ability to support Intel’s SSE instructions. The ability to use Intel’s instructions makes the chip that much more compatible with other chips and other PC’s in general. The meg of L2 cache is a nice addition to the chip but the Integrated memory controller is the selling factor of this chip. Since current chips don’t have it, it has to be built onto the motherboards north bridge chip, which can not run at the high speeds of say a P4 with Hyper Threading enabled, actually slows the CPU in high demanding processes, like 3d games. 3d games are in particular slowed since the processor has to send out to the north bridge chip and back to get the information it needs instead of being able to do it itself.  This CPU can also allocate much more memory than any 32-bit chip. A 32bit chip can only allocate up to 4gigs of memory, the Athlon 64fx can in theory allocate up to, are you ready for this, 256 TERABITES yes TERABITES. Why would we need this, I don’t know, unless you have been playing UT2K3 for weeks straight or plan to, we wont need this technology for a few more years.</p>
<p class="body">I know you all are wondering “How fast is it?” Since this is its first release, the FX will be a 2.2 GHz. Yes I know its no where near the 3.2 GHz P4c or P4ee but I believe with in several months this will be the chip in all top end gaming, video editing and server machines, and not a P4. AMD is not currently saying anything about the potential of this chip; they only say that speed is not everything. Now all you are left wondering is who is going to provide 64bit products. Well your normal companies are on the job, ASUS, MSI, ABIT, Gigabyte, DFI, and Chaintech will be making mobo’s available for the chip, and since you need a 64bit OS, a 64bit version of Windows XP is in the making along with a Linux OS. Also there is a planed 64bit version of UT2K3 for release.</p>
<p class="body">Now I’d hate to bust any bubbles about this chip but I feel I need to point out several things that might deter someone from going out now and buying one. For one thing you need a 64bit OS. Yes there is a new version of XP for that but it is still in beta testing and not available to the public. So the only thing you can use is a 64-bit version of Linux and if you are a serious windows person that isn’t going to make you happy, plus that too is also in beta so it has bugs. And I hope you know but just in case, the chip WILL NOT work in an old mobo. You should know that but I had to make sure.</p>
<p class="body">There’s more to come from me. Next time, Radeon 9800 vs. the 5900fx by Invidea.</p>
<p class="body"> </p>
<p class="citetext">All information found in the November issue of Maximum PC.</p>
<p class="body"> </p>
</body>
