<title>Behind the Display</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/samsunglcd.jpg</img>
<date>1/7/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Today, most monitor connectors come in one of two formats: VGA or DVI. VGA cables end in two 15-pin male DE-15 D-Subminiature connections, or D-Sub. Standard VGA, or Video Grid Array, uses voltages across the cable to represent the brightness of an area on the monitor. The scanning beam in the CRT then intensifies its frequency to produce the image. Often the cables for D-Sub connections are called VGA cables. D-Sub connections are still widely available on almost all graphics cards, projectors, and monitors, though the popularity of DVI allows some graphics card manufacturers to promote devices with no D-Sub connection.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/monitor_format/vga.jpg" alt="VGA Connection"><br><b>A typical VGA connection.</b></p>
<p class="body">Standard LCDs use a subset of the SVGA standard, usually XVGA (1024x768) or SXGA (1280x1024), but since the technology behind them is different, they have the ability to be used with DVI connections. DVI, or Digital Visual Interface, is purely digital. The only data coming through the cable is binary, telling the monitor which pixel to display at which brightness. If the monitor is not run at native resolution, it has to do some extra work to figure out the relative pixel sizes, a reason why native resolution is recommended as much as possible. An LCD using a D-Sub connector needs a decoder to translate the analog signal, of voltages, into the binary format the monitor understands. Since there is a translation, picture quality should theoretically suffer and distortion may occur. DVI connections have multiple standards, including formats for analog (DVI-A), digital (DVI-D), and combination (DVI-I) versions. The newest version, and very necessary for high resolution displays, is DVI-Dual Link. These connections can display up to 2560 × 1600 pixels, necessary for monitors such as Apple’s 30” Cinema Display. They push two pixels per clock, instead of the standard one pixel for other DVI versions. Single link versions can only output up to UXGA, or 1600x1280. </p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/monitor_format/dvi_connector600.jpg','600','416')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/monitor_format/dvi_connector600_sm.jpg" alt="VGA Connection" border="0"></a><br><b>A typical DVI connection.</b></p>
<p class="body">One other feature of DVI is HDCP. HDCP stands for High bandwidth Digital Content Protection. Some DVI connections feature this, and some do not. This inclusion of HDCP is one reason why many HDTV’s feature the DVI standard. When content is transmitted via the DVI cable, it is first encrypted to prevent unauthorized use.</p>
<p class="body">HDMI is an interesting connector in that it can be used for video and audio. HDMI Type A is backwards compatible with DVI, needing only an adapter. This supports up to resolutions of 1080p with only 19 pins. Type B can support higher with an additional 10 pins and is backwards compatible with DVI-DL. HDMI supports eight 1-bit audio channels for eight channel sound at up to 192 kHz. Video over HDMI is first converted to TMDS, or Transition Minimized Differential Signaling. TMDS is the basic signal transfer technology behind HDMI and DVI, with a 10-bit TMDS link providing 1.65 GB/s of bandwidth. For reference, this is enough bandwidth for a 1920x1280 display at 60 Hz. HDMI will also support HDCP.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/monitor_format/HDMI.jpg" alt="VGA Connection"><br><b>A typical HDMI connection.</b></p>
<p class="body">UDI is a new format being proposed, standing for Unified Display Interface. This format is meant to replace the analog VGA interface and will be compatible with DVI and HDMI. It will also use HDCP, making all formats on the market DRM capable. Vista is rumored to require a sort of DRM for at least High Definition video, or it will be scaled down to 480p, or DVD quality. UDI was announced only recently, with the UDI SIG (Special Interest Group) created on December 20, 2005. This newest format is not meant to compete with HDMI. Instead, it is meant to coexist, with HDMI focused more on consumer electronics and UDI focused on computers and graphics. UDI will not carry audio signals for this reason. However, the bandwidth available to UDI is about 16 GB/s, over three times that of the 5 GB/s for HDMI. This could mean that extremely high resolution displays are coming, or new display technologies that require much more bandwidth. Regardless, UDI sounds fairly future-proof.</p>
<p class="body">Another display format that was announced earlier, around May of 2005, was DisplayPort. A major selling point of this format is the small interface, being smaller than standard VGA and DVI. The backers of DisplayPort hope to push its technology into as many devices as possible, including notebooks. Providing up to 10.8 GB/s of bandwidth, this format would also include content protection, but not HDCP, instead using DRM being developed by Philips. HDCP was created by Intel’s subsidiary, Digital Content Protection, LLC. Analysts at Jon Peddie Research suggest that DisplayPort was created by the VESA (Video Electronics Standards Association) to specifically not include Silicon Image, a company providing IP and chips for HDMI and UDI. </p>
<p class="body">In conclusion, at least one thing is certain. VGA and its aging analog interface will soon be unsupported, soon being a relative term. Modern displays and video devices are being forced to support DRM, through HDCP or other schemes. New technologies such as Window’s Vista and Intel’s Trusted Computing Module will protect content as never before, while likely forcing users to upgrade hardware and software. </p>
<p class="body">Interestingly, both nVidia and ATi are backing DisplayPort, with nVidia supporting UDI as well. With other companies such as Dell and HP supporting DisplayPort, and Apple and Intel supporting UDI, the two formats will hopefully not conflict as badly as the current HD-DVD vs. Blu-Ray DVD war. It is my sincere hope that we will not have to deal with more than two standards, at least for the extra costs involved by putting more connectors on monitors and video cards. Simply by looking at the formats, UDI appears to be a better interface, with more compatibility and more bandwidth than DisplayPort. But in the tech world, surprises often happen, so we will have to wait and see.</p>
<p class="citetext">References:<br>
<a href="http://www.wikipedia.org" target="_blank">Wikipedia.org</a><br>
<a href="http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,1558,1813963,00.asp?kc=ETRSS02129TX1K0000532" target="_blank">ExtremeTech.com</a><br>
Images from:<br>
<a href="http://www.samsung.com" target="_blank">Samsung</a><br>
<a href="http://www.sfsu.edu/~avitv/computerfaq.html" target="_blank">San Francisco State University</a><br>
<a href="http://www.crutchfieldadvisor.com/ISEO-rgbtcspd/learningcenter/home/connections_glossary.html?term=DVI_jack" target="_blank">Crutchfield Advisor</a><br>
<a href="http://www.scientificatlanta.com/products/guidetoHDTV7.htm" target="_blank">Scientific Atlanta</a></p>
</body>
