<title>Dual Headache</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/s3.jpg</img>
<date>1/7/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">“Dual” seems to be the latest catch phrase in the tech world. Dual core processors are new and exciting. Dual graphics cards are new and exciting, but they’re not something I approve of.</p>
<p class="body">Dual seems to be a way to bypass limitations. By adding a second card, more performance is gained, and the company only has to sell one version of the card. Just buy two, and your performance is doubled! Or so they would like you to think. In reality, dual graphics solutions rarely give you an extra 100% boost in speed. More likely, they will top out around an extra 80%, which is not bad. But consider that some games won’t even reach 15% more speed. Some games may even run slower, if the improper mode is set. Is dual graphics worth it now? Maybe not.</p>
<p class="body">From a manufacturer perspective, dual is good. Instead of making ever larger processors, manufacturers can simply slap two of them together. SLi and Crossfire only require an extra connector, a switch flipped, and suddenly there’s more horsepower. Even small graphics player S3 jumped in with MultiChrome. Plus, to enable dual graphics, most consumers must go out and purchase new motherboards. These overpriced enthusiast motherboard chipsets are made by the same graphics players, nVidia and ATi, and they make even more profit. nVidia has also locked support for SLi to their own solutions, preventing Intel chipsets from being SLi capable. Now, users are forced to buy nVidia if they want SLi. The whole SLi licensing scheme doesn’t stop with nVidia products. Power supply, graphics card, and motherboard manufacturers pay to have the SLi-ready logo on their boxes. For nVidia, SLi is pure marketing genius. </p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/dual_headache/nvidia.jpg" alt="Nvidia SLi Ready Logo"><br><b>SLi Ready.</b></p>
<p class="body">But the consumer pays dearly for that extra performance boost. With at least 3 different variations on a single chip, and 3 different chip types per generation, the graphics market is already confusing for the average consumer. Dual graphics will only make it worse. With SLi, the exact same chip needs to be used for SLi to work. It used to be that the exact same card maker was needed, but current drivers should address that. With Crossfire, different chips of the same type can be used, but the faster chip will downclock to match the slower chip.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/dual_headache/ati.jpg','540','346')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/dual_headache/ati_sm.jpg" alt="ATi Crossfire" border="0"></a><br><b>An example Crossfire setup.</b></p>
<p class="body">Then there’s the price. Standard GeForce 7800 GTX cards run around $500. Two of them are an extraordinary $1000. Then the motherboard cost ($150) must be factored in. What if you don’t have a power supply capable of supporting SLi? Another $100. The newest 7800 GTX 512 editions cost much more, around $700. The Radeon X1800 512 is only $550. Expect master card versions to be more expensive. Of course, there are cheaper dual graphics solutions. SLi works on the $100 GeForce 6600 line. But two 6600’s, even two 6800’s, aren’t even capable of matching a 7800GT, which runs about $350. Buying the cards and the SLi motherboard would cost you about as much. So what’s the point in upgrading to cheap SLi?</p>
<p class="body">And then the drivers: sometimes they work, and sometimes they give you large black horizontal lines, artifacts, or bad textures. Admittedly, most games should work. But what if they don’t? When I buy the latest hot game, I expect it to work out of the box. I don’t want to have to tweak game profiles, or update drivers, or restart my computer three times just to get a game to work with my graphics cards. I don’t want to have to wait until the next driver release, either.</p>
<p class="body">Let’s face it: There are lots of things that we’d like to see differently in the graphics industry. For example, do we need a marketing term for antialiasing, one for texture compression, one for pixel shaders, one for… there’s just too many. Too many terms, too many versions of cards, and too many marketing tricks.</p>
<p class="body">With games like Fear taxing dual graphics setups already, it’s not all bad. But for the price I’d have to pay, I just don’t think it’s worth it.</p>
<p class="citetext">Images from:<br>
<a href="http://www.computerbase.de/news/hardware/grafikkarten/s3_via/2005/november/s3g_s20-serie_multichrome/" target="_blank">Computerbase.de</a><br>
<a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/?article=19595" target="_blank">TheInquirer.net</a><br>
<a href="http://www.ocaholic.ch/xoops/html/modules/news/index.php?storytopic=2" target="_blank">Ocaholic.ch</a></p>
</body>
