<title>Dell Inspiron E1705</title>
<author>James Smyth</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/e1705.jpg</img>
<date>3/4/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">If you're shopping around for a laptop, mobility should be somwhere in your mind. If mobility is your top priority, you might as well stop reading now. The Dell Inspiron E1705/9400 isn't the least portable notebook out there (it's relatively thin for a desktop replacement) but it won't fit anywhere on an airliner tray table. At a whopping 17" and 8.2 pounds, it is meant to stay mostly where it is and live off the life giving blood of a nearby power socket. If you're a business man on the go, you might want to consider the Inspiron 710M or B120. If you're a lanparty addict who needs power on the go at a decent price, this is exactly what you've been waiting for. You can really load this baby up with sweet specs without hitting even the baseline price of Dell's latest gaming laptop, the Inspiron XPS M170</p>
<p class="body">You are given two options for screens. The default screen is WXGA, which comes to 1366x768 pixels. This might be enough for the typical home user, but this notebook is designed for the power user and an extra $149 for 1920x1200 is easily worth the extra desktop realestate and improved graphical quality you gain. The extra cost will also get you Dell's TrueLife(tm) LCD, which is just a fancy name for anti-glare. While it might sound like bullshit, I wouldn't have believed the difference till I saw it. Most any monitor, be it CRT or LCD, will have overwhelming glare problems in direct sunlight, the same is not true of this LCD coating. Even in direct sunlight, the screen is amazingly crisp and easy to see. The only problem is if you have a dirty screen (Microfiber people! Don't touch an LCD with anything you wouldn't touch eyeglasses with!) cleaning it is much more of a hastle. So if you want a tougher screen, you might want to avoid this upgrade. The anti-glare basically works by lowering the refractive index of the light that hits the screen and requires a smooth finish instead of the matte finish most LCD users are familiar with. Unfortunately this means that your screen becomes almost like a mirror and dark movies will always show your reflection. For a hardcore technical breakdown of exactly how it works, check this out: <a href="http://www.screentekinc.com/pixelbright-lcds.shtml" target="_blank">http://www.screentekinc.com/pixelbright-lcds.shtml</a></p>
<p class="body">One place you'll have to make a sacrifice is graphics with the Geforce Go 7800. Dell wants you to buy their new fancy XPS M170, so only it has the Go 7800 GTX. But no worries, the Go 7800 is a great overclocker and RivaTuner will help you up the clock speeds to where they belong (note: overclocking can put your graphics card at risk and should not be attempted lightly). The Geforce Go 7800 by itself came to about the same performance as a Geforce 6600 GT. Overclocking I was able to get it to out perform the Geforce 6800 GT (desktop card), which is excellent for a laptop chip. And for only $300 extra between Intel's integrated chip and a Go 7800, you're getting the power of a 6800 GT at about the same cost as the desktop chip, which isn't bad at all. Especially considering that Dell offers the Go 7800 GTX on their laptop accessories page for $600, and the difference is about 8 pixel pipelines. As a note, RiveTuner will report 32 existing pipelines (24 pixel, 8 vertex) which would be better than the 24 total default pipes, but you can't unlock these without reseating the chip (not the board, but unsoldering and resoldering the chip itself). Here are the 3DMark scores I got:</p>
<p class="body">Dell Geforce Go 7800
<br>16 pixel pipelines, 6 vertex pipelines
<br>core:250, mem: 658
<br>3dmark03 - 9276
<br>3dmark05 - 3817
<br>3dmark06 - 2141</p>
<p class="body">Modified Go 7800
<br>core:346, mem: 886
<br>3dmark03 - 11517
<br>3dmark05 - 5190
<br>3dmark06 - 2869</p>
<p class="body">It is worth noting that if gaming is going to be your primary application, you really don't need a Duo core as the vast majority of modern games are still single-threaded and won't gain much from having a 2nd core. But you might have to go for a Duo anyway since the only Solo offered is at 1.66Ghz, which won't be enough for a hardcore gamer.</p>
<p class="body">The Duo is nice, but really has no use for anyone but the power user using supported applications. I don't notice any real performance difference between my dual-core laptop and my single-core desktop (which runs at a lower clockspeed). Certain applications such as Photoshop might benefit the most, but for the average user, there is no need to get anything more than the Solo. At 1.66ghz, it should be fine for MS Office, writing emails, browsing the web, and all those simple things the average user does. But at that point you have to ask yourself, why are you getting a desktop replacement? You might as well go for the 12" varient which will run longer on battery, run cooler, and is much more portable. The power user and gamer-on-the-go are the only markets targeted here.</p>
<p class="body">Assuming you are a power user with no need for games, I only have two upgrade suggestions for you. Duo (obviously) and the high-res screen as WXGA won't be enough for most power users. The same goes for the gamer, with the addition of the Geforce 7800, as the integrated Intel chip won't be good for anything more than Quake 3.</p>
<p class="body">Notes for Linux on the E1705:</p>
<p class="body">- The Intel graphics GMA 950 chip that comes by default will do 3D in Windows, but the official Linux driver from Intel only does 2D, and at that it will only run at up to 1600x1200, so there's no point in buying the LCD upgrade if you go with Intel. This may change as time goes on, but it isn't likely. Nvidia on the other hand is famous for their Linux support and is definately worth the extra cost.</p>
<p class="body">- The SigmaTel High Definition Audio is supported, but you will only get the absolute basics (master volume, line-in, and wave). It even lacks the ability to shut off the internal speakers when external speakers are plugged in. So headphones won't provide you with the privacy you'll want when using them. The audio control key combinations also don't work (they rarely do).</p>
<p class="body">- The Broadcom 440x 10/100 Integrated ethernet works just fine in Linux. If you want wireless built in, you'll want to go with the Intel upgrade as there are no Linux drivers for the Dell Wireless 1390 WLAN Mini-Card as of yet.</p>
<p class="body">- Everything else works just fine under Linux.</p>
<p class="body">So there you have it. The E1705 is a good buy for those looking for a desktop that fits (almost) in their lap.</p>
</body>
