<title>EB/Gamestop Merger</title>
<author>Jon Arnold</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/noimageavail.jpg</img>
<date>10/28/2005</date>
<area>gamer</area>
<body><p class="body">The only real "news" in the gaming community is the beginnings of a new monopoly on game pricing.  Electronics Boutique, due to it's loss of profits to the overbearing GameStop, has sold it's self to the largest gaming demon in current existence.  Save for the FuncoLand/EB merger years back this is the first significant merging of game retailers that could affect all of us.  So what are the implications of this merger?  Why should we care?  I'll tell you.</p> 
<p class="body">Since they became competitors EB and GameStop (GS for short) have had significantly different pricing options, as well as warranty options and discounts.  Let's take for example their "Used" item discount card.  While you save 10% across the board with both, EB's costs you less (by $10) up front.  Now sure, the difference between $5 and $15 may not be a lot to you or I, but I'm sure that there's someone out there that wishes they had an EB nearby after finding that out.  Now as for their warranties... I'm going to throw down for EB here only because I devised a way to exploit the system to make money off of their warranties, but that point aside (which I will explain later) EB had a good warranty system, and better coverage.  At EB, upon purchase of a new system, the clerk would ask if you want a warranty (costing you a mere $20 depending on the system's cost).  If you said yes, the money got tacked on to the price and you were covered for a year.  Anything you could possibly do to the system was covered.  You could throw it, hit it with a hammer, shoot it, crap inside of it (so long as you didn't break any of the warranty seals opening it), drop a brick (or large person) on it, anything you could possibly think of (I had a guy run his XBOX over with a truck and it was covered) is covered with this warranty.  Looking at GS's policy you'll see a huge difference... THERE IS NO EXTENDED WARRANTY!  You get the 90 day manufacturer warranty and that is a very narrow warranty (if you ever sneezed on it you've voided the warranty "we can't have SARS getting on our electronics, now can we?").  This is the first change since the merger.  EB no longer offers an extended warranty... so sad...  And the biggest change (that could affect the public) is the change of their wages.  You used to be able to go to GS or EB and start at about the same wage ($6.25-$6.50).  Now, since the merger the evil GS corporation has slashed it's wages across both companies boards down to $5.15.  Now I understand the fact that I shouldn't be complaining about minimum wage, but when I get a second job so that I can make a little bit of money, I'd like to actually make money.  At that wage I may as well go and wait tables.  As far as other changes (that won't so much affect the consumer) EB is adopting GS's pricing SKU thereby forcing every EB in the country to re-SKU all of the products that they have on the floor (upwards of 3000 in some stores).  That doesn't affect me, and actually kind of makes me laugh at all the EB employees that will be putting in wonderfully long hours off the clock to get that job done.</p>
<p class="body">Well I guess I'll end this bias rant now... so remember kiddies, EB/GS may be evil, but at least they've got better pricing that FYE (For Your Expense).</p>
<p class="body">Jon "I'm a fucking Ninja" Arnold</p></body>
