<title>Google It</title>
<author>Patrick Trinkle</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/google.jpg</img>
<date>10/25/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Google is fast becoming ubiquitous in the World Wide Web community.  If you somehow forget where you are or possibly where you're going there's Google Earth and Google Satellite Mapping.  Of Course The Google Maps use AJAX Technology which allows for a smooth load even if you're running dial-up and these users suffer very little ill-effect while surfing around the world.  Google Searching is customizable and if you use Firefox there is an even a custom Firefox Google Search.  You can also enter certain mathematical equations into Google and get answers.  You can search for images as well.  Google will scan pdf files, docs, xls, and other filetypes which has benefits and very strong downsides.  Google robots read through so much that they give away the whole bag of tricks.  This massive amount of indexed information can be parsed to find holes in websites and misconfigurations; just ask Johnny Long.  For those who don't like to delete emails, people like my father, there is Gmail whose individual capacity increases continuously.  When you want to shop online you might have in the past gone from website to website comparing prices, or possibly just checking your few favorites.  Now websites are sending product lists to Froogle which allows for very simple and range customizable searches.  You can have your news feed specialized and layout customized with Google News.  See Figure 1 for a display of current Google Tools.</p>
<p class="body">Google has begun the scanning of scholarly works for everyone, which will be very nice for researching papers.  Unfortunately if you write something similar to someone else this makes it even easier for Professors to accuse people of cheating on essays and projects.  On a similar note Google is getting in a lot of trouble by scanning in libraries of copyrighted texts for their Google Text.  On the subject of scholarly works there is Google Answers which allows you to buy answers by posting questions with a bounty.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('../../nsr_images/_articles/googleit/google_tools.jpg', '749', '236')"><img border="0" src="../../nsr_images/_articles/googleit/google_tools_sm.jpg"></a><br><b>Figure 1 Google Tools ( click to enlarge )</b></p>
<p class="body">For those people interested in, for lack of a better word, people—there are Google Blogs (which can be searched) and Google Groups.</p>
<p class="body">Maybe you just want to go out and get a scoop or maybe a drink.  If you can get a customizable Google frontend then why not make it localized?  They did, it's called Google Local.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('../../nsr_images/_articles/googleit/google_services.jpg', '685', '458')"><img border="0" src="../../nsr_images/_articles/googleit/google_services_sm.jpg"></a><br>
<b>Figure 2 Google Services ( click to enlarge )</b></p>
<p class="body">Before you think Google is some almighty powerhouse that wants the world for itself with its skyrocketing stock prices, Google has been pushing for Open Source research and projects, opening doors to young and old programmers with Sun and other companies.</p>
<p class="body">If you're beginning to wonder how Google, giving so much back, makes such high profits then you're wondering in the correct direction.  If you haven't seen Google Ads on a website then you're dumb, because if you look on this very website you'll find them.  Not only can you make money by putting Google AdWords on your website you can also bid money on certain words in searches.  If you ever wondered how certain websites get 1st place every time.  That has a lot to do with people paying money for key words in this giant of a search engine.</p>
<p class="body">People spend lots of money wanting to know what is happening with Google and what will come next!  I'm trying to stay ahead of the curve by the mere fact that I believe Google is getting too massive… kind of like skynet.</p>
</body>
