<title>Google Dominance</title>
<author>Patrick Trinkle</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/google.jpg</img>
<date>12/21/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Google is a powerful tool with an ever-rising stock price.  Companies are fighting to know how Google sorts its indexes and rates its websites.  Everyone wants to be the #1 result for a good keyword.  There is so much faith in Google’s methodology for indexing documents, that companies can buy two different Google Servers, the Google Mini for smaller businesses, and the Google Search Appliance, for enterprises.  More details on the Mini & Appliance Servers can be found under Google’s Business Services.  See Figures 1 & 2.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/googledom/googlemini.jpg" border="0"><br><b>Figure 1, Google Mini Server</b><br>
<img src="nsr_images/_articles/googledom/gsa_2u_rtside.jpg" border="0"><br><b>Figure 2, Google Search Appliance</b></p>
<p class="body">With the new Google Base, Google is heading in the direction of classified ad listing.  This will be competition for Ebay.  Google Base allows users to post their own content on the web.  As Google expands in the internet community it finds itself competing more and more with other companies already with an online presence, as well companies like Microsoft, which are beginning to invade the internet realm.  Google has quite a bit of a lead on Microsoft Live.</p>
<p class="body">Google is becoming more wirelessly integrated.  Now not only can you check your Gmail with your cellular phone, but you need either a friend with Gmail or a cellular phone to sign up for the service.  Gmail doesn’t use folders to organize information, but rather labels and with an increasing amount of space for messages you can afford to keep all your messages in the inbox.  The Gmail account can be tied in with your overall Google Account.  Google Accounts consolidate for a total Google experience.</p>
<p class="body">Now you can search Froogle in relation to where you are.  Not only does Google display competing stores prices based on your search criteria, but they also provide an interactive map, pinned with the stores’ information.  This can be very useful when trying to shop by price online restricting your search your locale.  The interactive map can be used to not only get store information such as the number for the store, but also get directions to the store from anywhere.  See Figure 3, Google’s Froogle Local Search.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/googledom/frogle_local_serach.jpg', '750', '498')"><img border="0" src="nsr_images/_articles/googledom/frogle_local_serach_sm.jpg"></a><br><b>Figure 3, Google’s Froogle Local Search</b></p>
<p class="body">With Google Base, Google Froogle, and Gmail users can fully utilize the internet for their own evil purposes.  If you run a business with a website, use AdSense for your advertising needs, and send your product feed to Froogle to open up the ecommerce market for you.  Froogle will parse the feed and produce sorted results for the user to allow for an extremely simple price comparison.</p>
<p class="body">In case providing awesome services to the internet community has drawn an obsessive or just loyal crowd, there is also a Google Store selling lots of crazy Google products, just like the Cafepress Network Stability Resource store.  For the record I honestly do not think their store is their primary income.  The job of Google's primary income appears to fall upon its ads.</p>
<p class="body">If you have a Gmail account you may have noticed ads tailored specifically to the email you're reading.  All over this site, ads are tailored to the purpose of the content on the page.  Google uses an interesting word engine that reads the content and matches it up to topics based on words on the page, and the frequency and context of the words themselves.  It's a fairly cool process.  Bidding on words in the Google search brings Google practically unlimited income, simply because of how many users rely on Google for their information.  As of December 19th opening bell, Google's Stock (GOOG) was at $424.60 or 573,294,917.28 TRL.  Google's stock has a 52 week range of 172.57 - 446.21 dollars.  It has been pretty much continuously on the rise, with only momentary dips along the way.  If you run a comparison of market value growth between Microsoft Corp. (MSFT) and Google, it is clear that Microsoft isn't growing as much as it is maintaining its current position (last trading at $26.83), whereas Google has soared over 300% increase.  For those of you who are lacking in imagination I have provided a very nice looking graph, generated by Yahoo, Inc. (It's funnier that way, trust me.) See Figure 4, Google vs. Microsoft provided by Yahoo Finance.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/googledom/googvmicro.jpg" border="0"><br><b>Figure 4, Google(blue) vs. Microsoft(red) provided by Yahoo Finance</b></p>
<p class="body">Few can say where Google going, and apparently they don't want the world to know.  Keep yours eyes open, because if you believe Microsoft to be an evil monopoly, perhaps Google will be an evil open-source monopoly, and the other internet information centers will be like Linux, another alternative, but not as ubiquitous.</p>
<p class="body">Furthering the idea of Google as a monopoly, deals are currently underway for Google, Inc to acquire a portion of AOL.  In this deal, AOL will have the ability to use videos ads within Google's Ad system, as well as allowing AOL Websites to be searchable via Google Search.  It was originally thought in early December that Time Warner would strike a deal with Microsoft Corp instead of Google, Inc, but this apparently is not the case.  Google's instant messaging service, Google Talk will allow users to communicate with AOL's ever-popular AIM (AOL Instant Messager).  This acquisition will strike a major blow in Microsoft Corp's attempt to gain land in the race for online focused office and mobility services as well as a powerful stake in advertising.</p>
<p class="body">How this will all end, or what will come of these recent events is hard to say at this point.  Perhaps good will come of such events, or perhaps the internet will go on a decline filled with advertisements tailored to the user.</p>
<p class="citetext">Information taken from:<br>
CNN Money http://www.cnn.com<br>
Yahoo Finance http://finance.yahoo.com<br>
Google, Inc http://www.google.com<br>
Images provided by:<br>
Google, Inc http://www.google.com<br>
Yahoo Finance http://finance.yahoo.com</p>
</body>
