<title>Hacking AIM</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/aim.jpg</img>
<date>12/28/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Special Note: The NSR, nor any of its writers, condones the use of the programs and techniques shown. </p>
<p class="body">When America Online launched AOL Instant Messenger in late 1997, it quickly became a smash hit. It was a new form of communication that took the world by storm. Today, more than five different protocols exist for Instant Messaging. AIM exists, firstly, as a marketing medium. At least 200 million people around the world use AIM, and that is a conservative number. Of those, most people still use the standard AIM client, which delivers pictorial and video advertising straight to the user. The emphasis, therefore, was on features, not security. As such, there are multiple ways of compromising the security of the standard AIM client. This article will provide a quick overview of some of the exploits in the 5.x version. The newest version, Triton, is not covered, but many of the same tricks can be done.</p>
<p class="body">The least malicious of all hacks is ad removal. AIM has particularly annoying ads, many of which come with loud sound bytes. For the coding inept, there is a mature hack that exists. As with all hacking, there may be unintended consequences. The easiest method of ad removal, but one that also cuts down on functionality, is to use a third party client, such as GAIM or Trillian. Some exploits must also be explicitly tailored to work with third party clients. <a href="http://www.jdennis.net/DeadAIM/about.php" target="_blank">Dead AIM</a> is a particularly popular AIM enhancement that also removes ads. The <a href="http://aftermath.dyndns.org:8888/~aimadhack/" target="_blank">AIM Ad Hack</a> is just for ad removal, and it now supports the newest version of AIM, Triton. Remember, AIM is supported by advertising.</p>
<p class="body">A more malicious exploit in AIM relies on bugs in the software. One of the most common bugs is bad XML/SML support, where others include icon exploits. This trick is called booting, where the AIM client is effectively shut down and the user kicked off. Code that can kill AIM looks like this:</p>
<p align="center"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/font.gif" border="0" alt="Malicious code"></p>
<p class="body">The standard AIM client cannot be used to send this faulty code, since it is converted to display those exact characters when sent. To crash AIM, another program should be used. Personally, I found the <a href="http://www.straylightrun.org/nemisis/index.php?page=programs" target="_blank">Nemisis</a> program, No Fear, to be an excellent introduction. </p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/nemisis.jpg','357','379')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/nemisis_sm.jpg" border="0" alt="No Fear"></a><br><b>No Fear 2.0</b></p>
<p class="body">Using the exact same code, it bypasses the conversion and will crash any AIM client from 5.2 to 5.9. The exploit works by sending this bad SML code with a chat invitation. Again, if you just type it in, the victim will just see that code above.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/nemisiscrash.jpg" border="0" alt="No Fear trying to crash GAIM"><br><b>No Fear trying to crash GAIM</b></p>
<p class="body">The screenshot demonstrates that GAIM is invulnerable to this particular exploit. Trillian is unaffected as well, but will not recognize it as bad code. For more functionality, and to be able to crash Trillian and GAIM, another program called Ghost Tool is available. This program is much richer in features, and necessarily more complex.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/ghosttools6.jpg','697','496')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/ghosttools6_sm.jpg" border="0" alt="Ghost Tool 6"></a><br><b>Ghost Tool 6</b></p>
<p class="body">Password hacking is the most malicious, and one that is beyond merely annoying. Many people often write that their AIM passwords have been compromised and they need to hack into their accounts, but somehow these users sound somewhat suspicious. Nevertheless, there are ways to hack passwords.</p>
<p class="body">The first, and often most successful method, is social engineering. In the world of security, the user is the first, and last, defense. Gullible   users are a malicious hacker’s wet dream. Putting together a professional sounding   email, or IM, from "AOL Administration" is not hard. As most AIM password   hackers will tell you, it is often easier to trick a user into giving up their   password. Based on a standard AIM message, an example of such a message might   be: "You have signed onto two different locations. Please enter your password   to sign off at the other location." You’d be surprised how effective something that simple might be.</p>
<p class="body">A second method requires much more. The hacker must have physical access to the user’s computer, and the user must have saved their password in the AIM client. Most people do this just to make things easier. For this, a simple program called Snadboy’s Revelation can be used. Snadboy’s Revelation is a tool to turn passwords hidden behind asterisks back into normal characters. Since AIM doesn’t have any particularly strong password encryptions, Snadboy’s Revelation does the job fine. </p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/snadboyandgaim.jpg','775','424')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/snadboyandgaim_sm.jpg" border="0" alt="Snadboy's Revelation"></a><br><b>Snadboy's Revelation failing to read the password correctly</b></p>
<p class="body">Snadboy is not just for AIM, but some programs might give it issues. With GAIM, Snadboy shows my password to be "Gaim.exe", which is it not.</p>
<p class="body">Also requiring access to the user’s computer is a tool which all users should beware of. A keylogger installed on the system will not only steal passwords, but also personal information, such as credit card numbers and social security numbers. Keyloggers are highly dangerous to your privacy, so make sure your anti-malware programs are properly updated.</p>
<p class="body">As noted before, AIM doesn’t have particularly strong encryptions. Available from many sites are packet sniffers specifically tailored to decode OSCAR packets. OSCAR is the protocol that AIM uses, a binary protocol standing for Open System for CommunicAtion in Realtime. Packet sniffers aren’t easy to use, but are effective.</p>
<p class="body">The final method of hacking passwords is using a program to find the password. Depending on the length of the password, or types of characters involved, it can be extremely tedious. </p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/cracking_aim/pooppwc.jpg" border="0" alt="Poop PWC"><br><b>Poop PWC: Hard to understand the interface</b></p>
<p class="body">The program above is called Poop PWC. At first sight, it is extraordinarily intimidating. Other popular password crackers include AIM Boss and Raven Underground. But like all password crackers, there are two methods of finding a password. The first is a dictionary attack, where the program checks to see if any of a list of words will work. This type of attack is highly reliant on a fully featured word list. The second attack is called brute forcing, where all possible character combinations are tried. This is the longest and most tedious attack available, but is more likely to succeed. Most people use common words or names for their passwords, but in the event that numbers or slashes are used in the password, this type of attack can find it. </p>
<p class="body">If your account for AIM has been compromised, and your password maliciously changed, it is often much easier to create a new account with a stronger password than to crack it and change it back. </p>
<p class="body">Again, we at the NSR do not support malicious use of hacking tools, pranks included. That being said, I hope that this was a good overview of the most common exploits for AOL’s Instant Messenger, and possibly an insight into software security.</p>
<p class="citetext">For more tools and programs, you can visit:<br>
<a href="http://www.aimfilez.com" target="_blank">AIM Filez</a> www.aimfilez.com<br>
<a href="http://www.aimkaos.com" target="_blank">AIM Kaos</a> www.aimkaos.com<br>
<a href="http://www.straylightrun.org/nemisis" target="_blank">Nemisis</a> www.straylightrun.org/nemisis</p>
</body>
