<title>The New PC: Laser Inside</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/lasers.jpg</img>
<date>12/20/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">In 1958, two researchers at Bell Labs created a revolutionary invention that slowly, gradually, became an essential part of American life. The invention was the laser, an invention so extraordinary that its uses are still being researched.</p>
<p class="body">What is a laser, exactly? Laser stands for Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation. Basically, the electrons in atoms absorb energy until they release photons, or light energy. Lasers are different than normal light, however. The light a laser outputs is typically of one specific wavelength, or monochromatic. With this one specific wavelength, all photons in the wave are move together along the wave, meaning it is coherent. The laser is also extremely directional, which gives it the intensity a normal flashlight lacks. Lasers typically come in one of four classes. Class I lasers are pretty much harmless, while Class IV lasers can start fires, or burn skin. Laser pointers fall under Class IIIA, hazardous when pointed in the eyes.</p>
<p class="body">Where are lasers, these days? Commonly, people think of laser pointers, useful for presentations, but more commonly used to annoy people. In manufacturing, lasers are precision tools used to cut hard materials or to etch beautiful patterns. At the supermarket, lasers are used to scan the barcodes on every item. The military is developing lasers for use in weapon systems, and recently, anti-missile devices have been created for use on domestic airliners. Lasers are also starting to play a role in medicine, whether in hair removal or experimental treatments.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/laser_inside/59s.jpg" border="0"><br><b>Laser etching, done as part of case mod Project KOS-MOS, by Bill Rider, at <a href="http://www.bit-tech.net" target="_blank">Bit-Tech.net</a></b></p>
<p class="body">In the world of computing, how do lasers play a role? We’ll start simple. Lasers are used in optical media drives, from CD’s to the new Blu-Ray discs. Logitech started the new laser mouse generation; with the venerable MX1000 being hundreds of times more accurate than normal red LED optical mice. But as technology progresses, lasers take aim at an even more crucial component than the mouse: the CPU.</p>
<p class="body">Today’s processors are made using photolithography, a standard process in manufacturing semiconductors. Using photo reactive material and light, an outline would be created, ready for chemical etching to remove the unwanted material. This isn’t a very efficient process, since there is a lot of chemical waste. With laser lithography, designs can be imprinted in material with features much smaller than the 35 nanometer gates in current processors. With shrinking of processors becoming more and more crucial to performance, this is a welcome development.</p>
<p class="body">New research is also studying the use of light interconnects instead of electrical pathways. Using tiny lasers to transmit data would probably be cheaper than creating 6 layer PCB’s and thousands of times faster than a current through wire, not to mention the benefits of smaller motherboards and less electrical interference. If you’ve taken a look at your motherboard, ever, you’ll notice just how many traces there are from the memory controller to your RAM. There are quite a few difficulties, though, when trying to design such a thing, so don’t expect that light computing will take off anytime soon. But this, unlike the Wankel Rotary Engine, is probably a sure thing of the future.</p>
<p class="body">Technology is always an exciting thing. The future always brings two promises: Faster, and Better. Lasers are just a new path we can take to get there.</p>
<p class="citetext">For more information about lasers, please visit the following:<br>
<a href="http://www.bell-labs.com/about/history/laser/" target="out">The Invention of the Laser at Bell Labs</a><br>
<a href="http://science.howstuffworks.com/laser.htm" target="out">HowStuffWorks: Lasers</a><br>
<a href="http://www.popularmechanics.com/science/defense/1281536.html" tareget="out">Popular Mechanics writing about Laser Weapons</a><br>
<a href="http://oemagazine.com/fromTheMagazine/jun01/linking.html" target="out">Optical Interconnects at OE Magazine</a><br>
Image Taken from:<br>
Project KOS-MOS, by Bill Rider: http://www.bit-tech.net</p>
</body>
