<title>Meeting December 17th</title>
<author>team</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/dec17brad.jpg</img>
<date>12/21/2005</date>
<area>activities</area>
<body><p class="body">We held this meeting to discuss the site's future, mostly focusing on the next step for the site, the store, and the changes and improvements on the site since the last meeting.  We also met to discuss the new layout of the forums area, which has yet to be... designed.</p>
<p class="body"><b>Meeting Minutes. December 17th</b></p>
<ol class="body">
<li><b>Introductions</b></li>
<li><b>New on the site:</b></li>
<ul class="body">
<li>the new important area</li>
<li>requirements for posting a new article</li>
<li>the colors of links for content</li>
<li>what to do with the 'coming soon' thing on the main page</li>
<li>retrofitting all articles with descriptions</li>
<li>to remove the cool lower left logo from the site, or add to all pages?</li>
<li>should we add the google search tool into the site, like just the search box?</li>
<li>need to change layout of personal area for use</li>
<li>forum layout(design only, the code is done)</li>
<li>more resources(links) need to be accumulated</li>
<li>need to add more features to personnel area</li>
<li>should we add the google-ads to every page?</li>
</ul>
<li><b>Publicity</b></li>
<ul class="body">
<li>an rss feed once we have lots of dynamic content and a large audience</li>
<li>should we try to get ads from companies like nvidia, etc?</li>
<li>need to contact thinkgeek, nvidia, etc</li>
<li>the newsletter</li>
<li>the flyers</li>
</ul>
<li><b>The Next Step with the site</b></li>
<ul class="body">
<li>need merchandise</li>
<li>ordering shirts for us</li>
<li>setting up the new store</li>
<li>new store layout, and organization of products</li>
</ul>
<li><b>Other</b></li>
<ul class="body">
<li>still need a macintosh writer</li>
<li>the nsr screenname</li>
<li>next team activity</li>
</ul>
</ol>
<p class="body"><b>Meeting Notes</b></p>
<ul class="body">
<li>Keep logo on the main page only</li>
<li>put links to forum entries the user made on the personal area of the site, to make it easier for users to follow discussions in which they're involved.<li>
<li>We will wait to contact any companies for advertising and cool gear until we're more popular</li>
<li>A friend of ours has some extra monitors which will be used for the next team activity, planned for the winter break.<li>
</ul>
<p class="body">Here are some photos from the meeting.  Brad wanted to note that Jim is wearing the same shirt as the last meeting...</p>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/patdec17.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/braddec17.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/georgedec17.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/jimdec17.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/jim2dec17.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="../nsr_images/_activities/jondec17.jpg" border="0"><br></body>
