<title>Meeting December 4th</title>
<author>team</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/dec4jon.jpg</img>
<date>12/4/2005</date>
<area>activities</area>
<body><p class="body">We held a meeting to discuss our first major move in the growth of this site.  Here's the agenda, the meeting notes, and some pictures.  Patrick is not in the pictures because he took the pictures.  The meeting was from 6:30-7:30PM, or somewhere around there.</p>
<p class="body"><b>Agenda for Meeting</b></p>
<ol class="body">
<li>Introductions</li>
<li>Cafepress, should we go Premium, features of premium presentation provided by Patrick</li>
<li>Site layout, presentation by Jim and his new layout ideas.</li>
<li>Behind the scenes work needed, presented by Patrick.  Delete messages, priveledge upgrade and restrictions</li>
<li>NSR newsletter in HTML format, it'll be cool.  Users when registering can opt to receive or not, and can change in user account area(not yet in existence-for stuff like changing email address, password)</li>
<li>Adding a suggestion box to the site(for site and articles)</li>
<li>Wearing a shirt for thensr.com is advertising, special shirts for writers/admins/etc</li>
<li>Kind of a shift from a tech help forum to a technology forum, possibly with a help forum.</li>
<li>We need a new writer for Macintosh, had to fire II because he didn't contribute.</li>
<li>Adding a cartoon?</li>
<li>Finding a moderator to run the forums.</li>
<li>Daily updates: news</li>
<li>Weekly updates: articles & cartoon(?)</li>
<li>Monthly updates: newsletter & activity</li>
<li>Staff required to run this site properly: 1 Administrator(Patrick); 1 PC Writer(Brad); 1 Linux Writer(Jim); 1 Macintosh Writer; 1 Moderator; all Technology Writers; 2 Gamer Writers(Jon & X); 1 Cartoonist?.  In reality more than one person can do a job, but at the same time I'm a fairly overworked administrator trying to run an advertising campaign & run the site.</li>
</ol>
<p class="body"><b>Meeting Notes</b></p>
<ul class="body">
<li>A larger staff area, with article editting places, and an area to allow for peer revision and comments for internal use only.</li>
<li>log-in to rate article</li>
<li>cafepress premium store 60$ a year, bascially sell 1 shirt a month to pay for it.</li>
<li>find someone to work with an online comic for the site.</li>
<li>size 1024x768 instead of 800x600, new layout, forums seperate & categorized</li>
<li>update to the shirt design</li>
<li>message of the day from each of us if we want, like a post it note, where you move what you wrote before to an archive, and then post something new, just something to the side</li>
<li>random security site link?</li>
<li>user account stuff</li>
<li>use first name on articles</li>
<li>automated hatemail</li>
<li>new articles each week</li>
<li>montly newsletter</li>
<li>monthly team activity</li>
</ul>
<p class="body"><b>Some Pictures of us hard at work</b></p>
<p class="body">
<img src="nsr_images/_activities/dec4Brad.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="nsr_images/_activities/dec4Jon.jpg" border="0"><br>
<img src="nsr_images/_activities/dec4Jim.jpg" border="0">
</p></body>
