<title>New Tech</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/newtech.jpg</img>
<date>4/1/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Every once in a while, it's nice to take a look back at how technology has progressed. Sometimes, this technology replaces inefficient methods, and sometimes, this technology only creates more complexity. Let's take a look at how technology has invaded some less talked about areas of life.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Paper Books - New Tech: eBooks</strong></p>
<p class="body">With computers invading everyday life, people had a brilliant idea. Why carry around twenty pounds of books, when all of that could fit into a slim, portable, electronic device? And so the eBook was born. While not exactly new, new ideas are coming out every day. eBooks today come in a variety of formats including RTF, DOC, TXT, LIT, PRC, and PDB . Various formats contain different amount of formatting and Digital Rights Management capability, as well as proprietary technology to lock the eBook to a specific device or program. This is one reason why eBooks never replaced print books, since there's a confusing variety of competing formats. Another reason is that electronic devices, specifically eBook readers, cause eye fatigue much more quickly than print books. With no real way to prevent this, eBooks just aren't as good as print books yet. Still, there are definite advantages, and I'm very glad that such things exist.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/book.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/ebook.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Print vs Tech. I like tech, but a bookshelf full of Dickens is more impressive.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Spray Paint - New Tech: Throwies</strong></p>
<p class="body">Nothing says graffiti like a wall covered in colorful spray paint. Gang symbols and various artworks abound in places like New York City, but a new form of graffiti is taking over: <a href="http://graffitiresearchlab.com/?page_id=17">Throwies (video link)</a>. A throwie is the geek's graffiti, comprising of an LED taped to a clock battery and a magnet. Throwies magnetically stick themselves to iron-based walls, providing a colorful and illuminating experience. Unfortunately, throwies only last a few hours, and can be expensive compared to paint. But the cool factor is definitely there. Check out <a href="http://www.graffitiresearchlab.com/">Graffiti Research Lab</a> for more on this.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/graffiti.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/throwies.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Paint Graffiti vs Throwies. Pity Throwies only last for a few hours.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Alarm Clocks - New Tech: Body Clocks</strong></p>
<p class="body">I've always thought that the best way to wake up in the morning is either by the smell of breakfast or the in the snuggles of a pretty girl. Unfortunately, real people usually don't have these luxuries and struggle to wake up to the sounds of an alarm clock. You've all seen the basic alarm clock with two loud bells on it, but have you seen the <a href="http://gizmodo.com/gadgets/gadgets/puzzle-alarm-clock-presents-mild-challenge-wakes-you-up-157999.php" target="_blank">puzzle alarm clock</a>, which makes you fit a puzzle together to make it stop? It's a creative, somewhat low tech, way of waking up. What about the <a href="http://alumni.media.mit.edu/%7Enanda/projects/clocky.html" target="_blank">Clocky</a> concept? It's an alarm clock that rolls away after snooze is pressed, making you wake up and find it. Interesting indeed, but it's still somewhat low tech. What you really need, then, is the Body Clock. These alarms use light to simulate the rising sun, using gradually more light until you wake up. People say that it's a better way to wake up, or at least not as abrupt and noisy.  I don't know if you'd like to spend $60 on an alarm substitute, though, but try it if you get the chance.</p>
<p class="body">I personally advocate <a href="http://www.bimbambanana.com/index.php?p=&side=visProd&prod_id=6">pitching your alarm clock</a> and waking up to the sun.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/rogerwood.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/bodyclock.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Alarm Clock vs Body Clock. Which would you rather have?</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Toilets - New Tech: Toilets.. but higher tech!</strong></p>
<p class="body"> Here's a fun toilet fact from Wikipedia: American President <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyndon_Johnson" target="_blank">Lyndon Johnson</a> would occasionally want to receive staff members while he sat on the toilet. Truth of the matter is, toilets are an essential part of civilized society. While there's already confusion over toilet differences between the US and Europe (bidets, anyone?), the Japanese have taken toilets to the next level. Toilets in Japan now offer voice reminders to wash hands, spray you with cleansing water, and come integrated with a blowdryer. For some, it's very cool, but for others, it can be embarrassingly confusing, especially when you don't know how to turn off the spray of water. If you ask me, I might just stick with my standard American toilet, for now.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/toilet.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/neorest.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">The Toilet Office vs the Neorest High Tech Toilet. I personally think the Neorest is much nicer.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Pets - New Tech: AIBO</strong></p>
<p class="body">Pets are really something. Fun, furry, and loveable, they give their owners the attention and devotion their kids won't. They are truly great animals, but they have huge drawbacks. Visits to the vet are very expensive, as can be their food. For the obsessive pet owner, clothes and treats can cut into the family budget a bit more than they'd like. Some families can't get a pet, as well, due to their living situation or allergies. There's really only one way to solve anything these days, and that's through technology. The wizards at Sony came up with something not quite furry, but still quite entertaining. The <a href="http://www.sony.net/Products/aibo/" target="_blank">AIBO</a> is a robotic dog with a hefty price tag of two grand. It is hackable, although Sony wishes it weren't. Other forms of entertainment robots are also available, such as the Roboraptor, available at a much cheaper $100. Still, these things have a fair way to go before they can replace that pet-shaped void in my life.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/cat.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/aibo.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Cat vs Dog. High Tech Robot Dog, that is.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Mule - New Tech: Robotic Pack Mule</strong></p>
<p class="body">While we're replacing animals with robots, we'll move on to the next category. Mules were once a mainstay in armies before GP's and HMMWV's, but became unpopular for various reasons. Extraordinarily strong, these creatures were also very intelligent. Perhaps too intelligent, since mules cannot be cajoled into running into a risky situation. They are animals, after all, and not only do they eat, but they can leave a rather smelly trail. The drawbacks of real mules might be why the US Army has invested millions into robotic pack mules that are able to go where vehicles cannot. One version, called the <a href="http://www.bostondynamics.com/dist/BigDog_Feb-26-2006.wmv" target="_blank">Big Dog (video link)</a>, is developed by Boston Dynamics. As videos show, it's pretty advanced, being able to carry quite a bit (40 kilos) and keep its balance even after being kicked. I don't think real mules like it, though.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/mule.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/bigdog.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Mule vs BigDog. I wouldn't buy either.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>Old Tech: Humans - New Tech: Robots</strong></p>
<p class="body">Why don't we go the whole way and replace humans with robots? Humans do evolve, but at a much slower rate than robots can. We already have fairly advanced artificial intelligence that can model the theories of mutation and natural selection. If you've ever played a tactical shooter, you'd see that sometimes AI is smarter than you are. AI is a hot area these days, and everyone's trying to get in on it. Companies and universities have developed programs that can converse like real humans, to varying degrees. As an example, try talking with <a href="http://www.titane.ca/concordia/dfar251/igod/main.html" target="_blank">iGod</a>. You'll understand that computers are far beyond simple numerical answers these days. But one of the best examples of robotic genius comes, oddly enough, from a car company. The people at Honda embody the principle of "think different" far more than Apple does, though it might not help their bottom line. These creative men and women have come up with inventions related to food crops as well as car technology, but it's truly the ASIMO that gets all the headlines. Able to greet people, it could one day be a versatile helper in homes. What else can it do? <a href="http://world.honda.com/ASIMO/" target="_blank">Take a look for yourself.</a></p>
<p align="center" class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/carriefisher.jpg"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/newtech/asimo.jpg"></p>
<p align="center" class="body">Carrie Fisher vs ASIMO. I think I know what I prefer.</p>
<br>
<p class="citetext">Images from:</p>
<ul class="citetext">
<li><a href="http://www.booksale.com.ph/bookimages/grisham_client.JPG" target="_blank">Booksale.com</a>
<li><a href="http://www.dailytech.com/article.aspx?newsid=1328" target="_blank">DailyTech</a>
<li><a href="http://www.visualresistance.org/wordpress/images/lee_epitaph1.jpg" target="_blank">Visual Resistance</a>
<li><a href="http://www.graffitiresearchlab.com/" target="_blank">Graffiti Research Lab</a>
<li><a href="http://www.educared.org.ar/tamtam/images/roger_wood.jpg" target="_blank">Educared.ar</a>
<li><a href="http://www.lumie.com/bodyclocks/index.htm" target="_blank">Lumie.com</a>
<li><a href="http://www.toiletmuseum.com/lgpic.php?photo=techno/soloviev2.jpg" target="_blank">The Toilet Museum</a>
<li><a href="http://www.damninteresting.com/?p=316" target="_blank">Damn Interesting</a>
<li><a href="http://mfrost.typepad.com/.shared/image.html?/photos/uncategorized/sukliz0r1e024.jpg" target="_blank">Cute Overload</a>
<li><a href="http://www.sony.net/Products/aibo/" target="_blank">Sony</a>
<li><a href="http://www.lovelongears.com/about_mules.html" target="_blank">LoveLongEars.com</a>
<li><a href="http://www.newscientist.com/channel/mech-tech/dn8802.html" target="_blank">New Scientist</a>
<li><a href="http://www.movie-gazette.com/directory/img/carrie+fisher.jpg" target="_blank">Movie-Gazette.com</a>
<li><a href="http://world.honda.com/news/2005/c051213_1.html" target="_blank">Honda</a>
</ul>
</body>
