<title>Microsoft's Office Live</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/office.gif</img>
<date>2/18/2007</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body>
<p class="body">The name Office Live would suggest that Office Live was a competitor to the highly successful Google Docs.  It is a misleading name, since Office Live is a business webhosting service.  The intended use of Office Live is to provide a web presence for businesses, along with the basic tools necessary for administration.</p>
<p class="body">There are currently three levels of Office Live: Live Basic, Live Essentials, Live Collaboration, and Live Premium.  Live Basic offers 5 free email accounts, a custom domain (served by Melbourne IT), and a basic webpage, and is entirely free.  This package comes with 30 MB of web space and 10 GB of bandwidth.  At $20 a month, Live Essentials offers some collaboration tools and customer information tracking.  For a little more, Live Collaboration adds more collaboration tools and removes some customer tracking features.  At $40 per month, Live Premium adds mobile email access, project management, and much more space.  Those interested should note that domain name registration is free, but websites are locked to the Office Live templates.  The email service is hosted by Office Live Mail, a clone of the Hotmail evolution, Windows Live Mail.  Advertisements display on the Office Live website, but not on custom domains.  A small "Office Live" badge is the only indication that Office Live was the host.</p>
<p class="body">Using Office Live is extremely easy, if a little slow.  The pages are very heavily scripted, making load times in Internet Explorer 7 a little long.  It is impossible to access the site in <span class=SpellE>FireFox</span> due to the ActiveX controls necessary.  Website customization is available, but websites are created using premade templates.  There is no HTML or CSS support available, a definite drawback.  Everything is extremely simple to use, however, a tradition that Microsoft has started with the new Office 2007.  There are some tools for website monitoring, such as simple trackers, but sophisticated website tools are missing, such as keywords, linkers, and search terms, which are available on free <span class=SpellE>WordPress</span> blogs.  In keeping things simple, Microsoft may have skimped a little on the tools true online businesses need.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/office_live/officelive_pageediting.jpg','640','484')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/office_live/officelive_pageediting_sm.jpg" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body" align="center"><i>Office Live does not offer much in the way of customizability</i></p>
<p class="body">It should be noted that Office Live is still in Beta, although it should be close to being released, as it has been in development for more than a year.   There are errors that occasionally affect usability, such as this one: "<span style='font-size:8.5pt;font-family:"Verdana","sans-serif"; color:#333333'>Your account setup is taking longer than usual. Try again in a little while.</span>"  In using Office Live, I have experienced times when web design changes are ineffectual, pointing to server issues.  Also, alternative browser support is limited.  Some website elements will not display, such as the Weather element, except in Internet Explorer.  And as usual, there is the occasional crash.  Overall, the beta is stable enough, but it could be better.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/office_live/officelive_messingup.jpg','640','484')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/office_live/officelive_messingup_sm.jpg" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body" align="center"><i>Office Live could use more compatibility.</i></p>
<p class="body">It is clear that Microsoft is branching away from traditional Office and Windows sales.  Office Live is a branch that attempts to offer Microsoft’s expertise in business software and push it to the inexperienced small business.  In this, it appears that it is successful in its goal.  Office Live will be perfect for "Martha's Antiques."  It will not satisfy the tech-savvy users, but it offers a great deal to the beginner.  There are a few problems, but it is still a beta, after all.  And the Basic package has an excellent price: free.</p>
<p class="body">You can find out more about Office Live <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/officelive" target="_blank">at the official website.</a> </p>
</body>
