<title>Why are they Popular?</title>
<author>James Smyth</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/tux.jpg</img>
<date>1/24/2006</date>
<area>linux</area>
<body><p class="body">There are literally hundreds of Linux Distrobutions in the sea of software, maybe a dozen with much popularity. Why can't we all just agree on one distrobution to rule them all? For more reasons than there are calories in a Big Mac. We'll take a look at the top and most ground breaking distrobutions today.</p>
<p class="body">Ubuntu: Ubuntu shot into our world from the clear blue sky and blew the newbie world away. Ease of use was always the order of the day for people new to Linux, and the mostly console based approach to installing software kept many at bay. While based on Curses rather than a full GUI, Ubuntu had a clean and easy installer. If you didn't care for dual booting you pretty much just hit enter a bunch of times and you're running Linux! While the software organization tool Synaptic had been available to Debian for some time, Ubuntu made it integral to the system so new users could jump right into everything Linux had to offer.</p>
<p class="body">Mandriva: Mandriva is result of a merger between Mandrake and Connectiva, but the Mandrake elements survived the most. Mandrake was originally based on Red Hat, but the key difference was that it was the first distro based on KDE. With the new user surge at the turn of the century, Mandrake was able to gain almost instant popularity. The Mandrake Control Center was a major reason people kept coming back, as many considered it the best freely distributed system manager for any Linux distro. Not much new has been happening with Mandriva and most now use it out of loyalty and familiarity.</p>
<p class="body">SUSE: In the world of commercially available distros, SUSE stands as one of the greats. The graphical installer and YAST (Yet Another System Manager) made it an early success. While Mandrake also had a graphical installer and system manger, SUSE's version tended to be better supported and visually slicker.</p>
<p class="body">Red Hat/Fedora: Red Hat was the first popular commercial distrobution. What made it a success where others had failed was with RPM, the first package managment software for Linux which was the first 'easy' way to get users started with Linux. Red Hat has since gone entirely commercial and now only sponsors a freely available distro called Fedora. Fedora has remained popular mostly because of the history behind it and the simplicity it offers.</p>
<p class="body">KNOPPIX: Knoppix was one of the most ingenious moves ever made in the history of Linux and opened the kiddy-pool to people who weren't quite ready to make the dive. Knoppix lets you boot and run a full Linux distro off of a CD-ROM. This meant that if someone wanted to give Linux a shot, but didn't want to play around with partitioning, Knoppix was the answer. Knoppix became used for many more things as it became popular. It started carrying system recovery tools and security applications so people in various feilds could use it for a variety of tasks (lord knows tools on Knoppix have saved my system on many occasions). Not everyone in IT uses Linux, but there's no excuse for anyone to NOT have a copy of Knoppix sitting around. In the years since it first hit the net many variations of it have cropped up from versions focusing entirely on security tools called Knoppix-STD (Security Tools Distrobutions)  to the FreeBSD version 'Freesbee'.</p>
<p class="body">Debian: Debian, a spawn of Slackware, was an early success for the people who didn't want hand-holding and didn't want to sacrifice power for the sake of ease. Debian was and always will be a power-user's distro. Debian is for the practical guru who knows how to use Linux and use it to its full power.</p>
<p class="body">Gentoo: Gentoo is like Debian in that it's made for power users. But unlike Debian, Gentoo is for the patient user who wants to learn while using. Gentoo isn't a distrobution in the classical sense, as it provides no installation software. Instead, the CD you burn is a quick and dirty bootable Linux shell. Through the shell you partition, format, and mount your root drive by hand and download a tar ball with all the basic software. Installation is simply going to root and untarring it, now you've got the kernel, a terminal, and a few other things you need to get going. The whole process teaches the user a lot about how Linux works in general and really puts what other distros do into perspective. While setting up a system can take literally days for the new user (I'm talking about new to Gentoo, anyone new to Linux would have no hope of making their way through), the end product is something you yourself made and carries with it a certain sense of pride and accomplishment.</p></body>