<title>Inside the Power Supply: the Anatomy of a Failed Unit</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/header.jpg</img>
<date>12/9/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">What does it take to bring down a power supply? Fellow writer Jim Smyth and I both experienced power supply failures, within a week of each other. So today, we took them apart, to show you what goes wrong, and why.</p>
<p class="body"><b>The Contenders:</b></p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/contenders.jpg', '542','415')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/contenders_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
<b>On the left is a Powmax 400W unit; the right, a Thermaltake 430W unit.</b></p>
<p class="body"><b>The Thermaltake:</b></p?
p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake.jpg', '442','342')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
The Thermaltake unit came in a pretty complete package. Besides a nice black finish and dual 80mm fans, the PSU came with a lot of connections: 2 SATA plugs, 3 chains of regular molex connectors, a 20+4 motherboard connector, all wrapped in nice plastic braid. As you can see, the connectors are long enough for large cases. The voltages, wattage, and general look and feel seem to indicate quality.</p>
<p class="body">Last week, my friend Jim experienced a power supply failure. Smoke was coming out of the back, a clear indication. At first, we were surprised. Compared to Jim’s purchases of $10 PSU’s, this was a clear brand name known specifically for quality. Thermaltake shouldn’t have failed so quickly, not after just four months of use. What exactly happened in that black box? We decided to investigate.</p>
<p class="body">As a side note, I would like to say, taking apart a power supply can be extremely dangerous. If you have any doubts, don’t do it. We also had help from two physics majors, helping us to avoid electric death. In the video, they have a discussion about an unknown component.<br>
<a href="nsr_images/_articles/physics.avi" target="_blank"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/smart.jpg" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-cover-off.jpg', '520','313')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-cover-off_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
The Thermaltake unit seemed alright, at first glance. The heatsinks are decent and the airflow should be adequate. Everything still indicates a quality unit. The transformer in this PSU is fairly large.<br>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-voltage.jpg', '288','419')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-voltage_sm.jpg" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-theproblem.jpg', '381','433')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/thermaltake-theproblem_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
Here’s where we noticed the problem. Look carefully, at the large, black toroid core inductor. [Note: A toroid core inductor is basically an iron ring wrapped in wire. The inductor stores magnetic energy, preventing changes in current.] The smoke was probably caused by the white thermal material burning. Next to it is a burst capacitor, never a good sign. A smoky smell was in the air for about a day before the PSU died, it was probably the capacitor that made the final cut.</p>
<p class="body">Why did the power supply fail? Overheating is probably the reason, since clearly, the ventilation failed to prevent heat from damaging capacitors and inductors. Jim admitted he ran the computer at full load for two weeks, but a water cooled case shouldn't have problems with heat build up like this.</p>
<p class="body"><b>The Powmax:</b></p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax.jpg', '436','224')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
Unlike the Thermaltake, nothing good can be said about this power supply. The label calls it an “ATX Switching Power Supply”. No brand name makes me think that the manufacturers were scared to put their name on this thing. Is it that bad? Yes. This thing feels like it barely even weighs a pound!</p>
<p class="body">The Powmax came in a Powmax case, the reason why I believe it was made by Powmax. The unit had fairly short cables, and few connectors. This thing barely had enough connection to power 4 IDE devices and the motherboard, let alone the GeForce 6800GT or the 8 fans in the case. I once took a look at the voltages this thing put out, and they were all under spec, at least 5% too low. Comforting? No. I wasn’t exactly surprised that this unit failed, it was only a matter of time.</p>
<p class="body">When I woke up one morning, I smelled a slight burning smell. The night before, I thought it was the heater, but I decided I should check the computer this time. Indeed, the burning smells came from the power supply. Even turned off, the burning smell lingered. Rapidly, I bought a FSP Power supply off of Newegg, and then the fun began. This dud was coming apart. Remember to wait at least 12 hours before opening a power supply, and even then it can be dangerous.</p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-cover-off.jpg', '564','467')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-cover-off_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>Take a look at the heatsinks on this PSU. They are extremely thin, with holes cut in the tops. We speculated that the holes were to increase surface area, somehow, or to move air differently. Since the air would be flowing straight across the heatsink, the holes could only serve to redirect airflow in unwanted ways. There are two transformers, like in the Thermaltake, but of much smaller size. The main transformer is about half the size, just one reason why the voltages were much too low.<br>
<a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-voltage.jpg', '240','350')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-voltage_sm.jpg" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-theproblem-1.jpg', '559','366')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-theproblem-1_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
Like the Thermaltake unit, the Powmax experienced similar difficulties. The capacitors in this picture are clearly dying, with browning at the tops and some strange goop promoting a sense of communal death.</p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-theproblem-2.jpg', '376','313')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/broken_powersupplies/powmax-theproblem-2_sm.jpg" border="0"></a><br>
The problems don’t end there, though. Although similar in spec to the Thermaltake’s two main capacitors, the Powmax’s main capacitors were of low quality. They were leaking, a very, very bad sign.</p>
<p class="body">Why did this power supply fail? Poor quality, which caused the eventual overheating. I’ll have to admit I was impressed it lasted six months, but seriously, this is one bad power supply. If I were to try to run it at full load for two weeks, I think I’d fail.</p>
<p class="body"><b>Conclusion:</b></p>
<p class="body">Looking at power supplies, there is usually a strong correlation between price and quality. Units from companies like PC Power and Cooling, Antec, and OCZ are expensive for a reason: they are least likely to fail under normal conditions. Even under stressful conditions, such as lengthy times at full load, they probably would survive. Quality components do make a difference, as do innovations in design.</p>
<p class="body">We aren’t often able to afford the best, however. Most people buy power supplies in the $50 range, avoiding the worst of the power supplies and getting something fairly reliable. But as Jim proved, these power supplies still will fail. When purchasing computer parts, most people don’t think about the power supply. The latest processor, or the fastest graphics; that is what people spend money on. People don’t expect their power supply to destroy their motherboard with improper voltages, or other such catastrophes. They will happen, though, if you aren’t careful.</p>
<p class="body">The moral of today’s story is this: your power supply is important. Choose wisely.</p>
<p class="body"><b>Things to consider:</b></p>
<p class="body">Power supplies are usually rated to last 100,000 hours at 25 degrees Celsius, or 77 degrees Fahrenheit. How often is it just 25 degrees in your computer case? I don’t know about yours, but mine is higher than that, usually around 30-35 degrees.</p>
<p class="body">When looking at power supplies, consider the weight. The heavier the power supply, the larger the heatsinks. Usually it’s a good indication of quality.</p>
<p class="body">Often, the Wattage of your power supply isn’t as important as the Amperage. If you have a 300W power supply that can put out 20A on the 12V rail, it’s already a lot better than a 400W power supply that can only put out 13A on 12V rail. The 12V rail is probably the most important, since your processor, video cards, and fans pull most of their power off of this. Remember, Amps x Volts = Watts: if your power supply advertises 400W and the specs only add up to 385W, something’s not right.</p>
<p class="citetext">If you want to know more about the parts in power supplies, visit this link at PCGuide: <a href="http://www.pcguide.com/ref/power/sup/parts.htm" target="_blank">http://www.pcguide.com/ref/power/sup/parts.htm</a><br>
Photos taken by Jim(NSR Staff)</p>
</body>
