<title>Power around the world</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/alert.jpg</img>
<date>3/4/2007</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">The modern world is one that enables people to travel easily to places exotic and common. Traveling may not require all the technology that is required at home, but somehow technology will undoubtedly come along for the ride. From digital cameras to electric toothbrushes, it is important to know what kind of electrical power one can expect to find around the world. After that, a simple check will determine if devices will work.</p>
<p class="body">When traveling, be aware of two things: voltage and frequency. Europe, Asia, Africa, and Australia predominantly use the 220-240V, 50Hz standard. A few countries, such as South Korea or the Philippines, use the 60Hz standard, which is more efficient. Japan uses an entirely different voltage, usually about 100V. Japan is odd in that two sides use different frequencies: Western Japan (Osaka) runs on 60Hz while Eastern Japan (Tokyo) runs on 50Hz. The Americas predominantly use 110-120V, 60Hz electricity, but South America varies depending on the region. <a href="http://users.pandora.be/worldstandards/electricity.htm" target="_blank">Conrad H. McGregor</a> has a very nice summary and world map for those who are interested in specifics.</p>
<p class="body">Fortunately for most technology users, modern power supplies, or 'power bricks,' are usually rated to handle voltages from 100-240V and frequencies of 50 and 60Hz. This means that your laptop or GPS device can plug into any socket worldwide with the appropriate socket adapter. For less advanced devices that are developed for a specific country, you may want to check the voltage and purchase a transformer for your device. Note that a converter is usually not enough for sensitive equipment, but it is probably good enough for a hair dryer. </p>
<p class="body" align="center"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/power/Poweradaptor.jpg" border="0" alt="Power Adapter Label"><br><i>These are the numbers you are looking for. Devices with these exact numbers can go anywhere.</i></p>
<p class="body">What happens if your device is dependent on a single frequency? Some devices, such as clocks and timers, will not function properly (i.e. display the wrong time) since the function is based on the frequency of electrical current. Some devices will work slower, such as the fan in a hair dryer. Other devices, such as battery chargers, will be fine since the device can adapt. You should be aware that transformers and converters are unable to change frequencies, so buy your devices carefully if that is an issue.</p>
<p class="body">Is it alright to use a device with a different voltage than was meant to be used? It depends. A voltage difference of 10 or so, in the case of Japan and the US, is probably not too bad, since voltage also can change depending on the distance from a main transformer. Don’t try it with anything too sensitive, but it should be ok with most appliances. A difference of 110, in the case of the US and Europe, is dangerous! Don’t even try it.</p>
</body>
