<title>Secure Mobile Browsing, for Free</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/secure.gif</img>
<date>2/11/2007</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body"><a href="http://www.hamachi.cc/" target="_blank">Hamachi</a> is one of the few extremely useful and extremely innovative products to appear in the past few years.  If you still don’t know what Hamachi is, it is a virtual private networking tool.  Each computer gets assigned a unique IP code that can connect to user based networks.   Since the client gets network data from the main Hamachi servers, there’s no need to fiddle with IP addresses or ports.  Also, the connection is encrypted between computers, making it a very secure connection.  Hamachi comes with a free secure proxy built in but it requires a subscription for anything more than 10 MB of traffic per month.</p>
<p class="body"><a href="http://www.privoxy.org/" target="_blank">Privoxy</a>, on the other hand, is a pretty handy tool, but nothing special. Privoxy is a free proxy tool that allows users to create an HTTP proxy on their computers.  There’s nothing encrypted, so it is fairly insecure on its own.</p>
<p class="body">Now, assume that a mobile user is on the road.  Hamachi allows them to VPN into their home network, where they can use tools like Virtual Network Computing or Remote Desktop Connection to securely browse the web from another computer.  But users like me find that to be a big hassle, as well as a little laggy.  RDP is a great tool, but it’s just not fast enough for me.  Also, downloading files is a little tricky, since files would be on another computer and more tools would be needed to get the files from there.  Add Privoxy into the mix, and the problems are solved.  Privoxy can be used to create a proxy on the home computer, where the connection is assumed to be secure.  Hamachi can connect the mobile computer with the home computer with an encrypted connection.   Now you can have secure computing that is pretty easy to set up.</p>
<p class="body">First, users need to download and install Hamachi and Privoxy.  Start Hamachi and get an IP address assigned.  Don’t start Privoxy yet.  Opening the Privoxy Main Configuration (config.txt) file, you’ll see a “Section 4.1: Listen Address” section.  To set Privoxy, insert a line like this: listen-address (Your Hamachi IP):8118. </p>
<p class="body"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/secbrowse/privoxysetup.jpg" border="0" alt="Privoxy Setup"></p>
<p class="body">Now, get your mobile computer out.  I like to use a tool called FoxyProxy to setup proxy connections in FireFox.  This alone is incentive for using FireFox instead of Internet Explorer on the road, since IE setup is similar, but can be a hassle when disabling or re-enabling the proxy.  You can also set up FoxyProxy to use Tor, an anonymous proxy, but Tor is often bogged down by traffic and can be extremely slow.</p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/secbrowse/foxyproxysetup.jpg','640','318')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/secbrowse/foxyproxysetup_sm.jpg" border="0" alt="Foxy Proxy Setup"></a></p>
<p class="body">Now, all you have to do is set FoxyProxy to run the proxy whenever you’re on the road and set it back when you are at home.  Free and secure browsing, all at the click of a button.  Really.</p>
</body>