<title>AMD Sempron</title>
<author>Patrick Trinkle</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/sempron_logo.jpg</img>
<date>1/2/2006</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body><p class="body">AMD (Advanced Micro Devices), Intel's chip competitor, has released a powerful new alternative to Intel's Celeron D.  The maximum capabilities of the AMD Sempron are 512 kilobytes of cache, a 333 MHz FSB (front-side bus), the 3DNow! graphics technology, and an integrated DDR memory controller, as well as Enhanced Virus Protection with certain operating systems.  Much like the Intel Celeron class of chips, the Sempron is designed for low-to-mid level computing, such as word processing, internet surfing, and leaf peeping.  If your intent is to run games like Doom III, this chip is not for you.  The AMD Sempron is a low-price chip for entry-level computer buyers, and those who do not have to do advanced mathematics and number crunching with their at-home computer.  Don't let its inability to do high level computing stand in the way of you purchasing this piece of hardware, as it can still kick some serious ass.  It's also not very expensive, as it runs $99.99 at CompUSA.  The Enhanced Virus Protection is utilized by recent operating systems, and the user must enable this feature.  The Enhanced Virus Protection is not a replacement for antivirus software, but rather a defense against buffer overflow attacks, which are executed by placing code into another programs memory space.  This is prevented by using an NX bit, or No eXecute, which is set so that on a program's data can be in that memory and not instructions.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/sempron/amd_semprons.jpg','640','480')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/sempron/amd_semprons_sm.jpg" border="0" alt="AMD Sempron"></a><br><b>Two AMD Sempron Chips at CompUSA</b></p>
<p class="body">The Sempron is backwards compatible with all existing 32-bit code.  The integrated memory controller has 64-bit DDR SDRAM at 100-200 MHz, and supports up to 3 unbuffered DIMMs.  The memory controller has double-bit detect and single-bit error correct.  The HyperTransport technology is a 16-bit link of up to 3.2 Gigabytes/second bidirectional.  The chip has multiple low-power states, and is built to utilize 754 pins.  The chip runs from 1667 MHz to 2000 MHz, with 128-256 kilobytes of L2 cache.  The system bus runs up to 6.4 Gigabytes/second.  90 Nanometer technology is comparable to the Celeron D (478 pin).  Unlike the Celeron D, which runs at 73W, the Sempron runs at a low-power 62W.  AMD benchmarked the AMD Sempron 2800+ as faster than the Intel Celeron D 2.8 GHz.</p>
<p class="body">In case you were under the impression the AMD Sempron is only meant for the desktop user, you are missing its highest relative performance per power usage.  The Mobile Sempron comes in two versions, the version for full-size notebooks, and the version for lightweight notebooks.  The Mobile Sempron also has the Enhanced Virus Protection.  If you're looking to buy a mobile Sempron, higher model numbers equal better overall performance.  The mobile Sempron is shipped with AMD's PowerNow! Technology.  PowerNow! Technology controls the power used by the computer based on the momentary needs of the laptop.  This can extend battery life by up to 65%.  PowerNow! runs automatically, and there is also software avaiable for the user.  This software is the PowerNow! Dashboard and displays the voltage, clock speed, and the battery life.  The mobile processor is compatible with 802.11a, b, and g.  The mobile Sempron runs from 1.6 GHz to 2.2 GHz with 128-256 kilobytes, running at 62W.  The mobile Sempron Light only runs up to 2.0 GHz, but runs at a very low 25W.  The Intel Celeron M is dwarfed by the Mobile AMD Sempron in performance, though the Celeron M runs on only 21W.</p>
<p class="body">In my opinion, without having one of my own, I would go for the AMD for a notebook over the Celeron M, but not necessarily for the desktop.</p>
<p class="citetext">For more information:<br>AMD Sempron <a href="http://www.amd.com/us-en/Processors/ProductInformation/0,,30_118_11541,00.html" target="_blank">www.amd.com</a><br>Wikipedia<br>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sempron" target="_blank">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sempron</a><br>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NX_bit" target="_blank">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NX_bit</a></p>
</body>
