<title>Shmoocon 2006 Day 2</title>
<author>Patrick Trinkle</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/shmoo.jpg</img>
<date>1/15/2006</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">I woke up at 0530 so I could drive up to New Carrollton Station by 0645.  Needless to say, I really didn't sleep the night before, and as such was too tired to drive.  So I caught a ride.  It only took about half an hour to travel through the fog and arrive at the Metro Station.  I boarded the Orange line to Union Station, and ran upstairs to catch the red line towards Shady Grove.  I didn't realize at the time that the train sitting there about to leave was one I could take.  Therefore I didn't catch it, but waited 15 minutes for the next one.  Three or four stops down the road I found myself very far underground.  Until then I had always assumed there was a limit to the slope of an escalator.  Now I know just what that limit is.  I registered after waiting around uncomfortably in the hotel lobby.  Mind you the Marriot is very nice here, and I was approached several times asking if I needed assistant.  And Day 2 of Shmoocon 2006 begins.</p>
<p class="body">If you're not familiar with Shmoocon, here is some background information.  Shmoocon is the wireless convention, and is convienently held on the east coast.  It is broken up into 3 sections, Build It!, Break It!, and BoF It!.  For more information on what they are specifically, see their website: <a href="http://www.shmoocon.org" target="_blank">Shmoocon</a>.  Once at the Marriot Hotel, where it was held this year, I register.  They give me a very nice bag and some other swag.  The badge for the con is a piece of cut sheet metal.  It's rather sharp, and some attendees were cut, and it became a common joke that if you flew here, you'd have to leave the thing behind.  They also gave us a very cool bag, Shmoo balls, and stickers.</p>
<p class="body" align="center"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/shmoocon2006/badge.jpg','600','450')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/shmoocon2006/badge_sm.jpg" alt="Shmoocon 2006 Badge" border="0"></a><br><b>Badge of Cutting</b></p>
<p align="center" class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/shmoocon2006/bag.jpg','600','450')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/shmoocon2006/bag_sm.jpg" alt="Shmoocon 2006 Bag" border="0"></a><br><b>Bag of Holding</b></p>
<p class="body">Saturday began very early, with administrative remarks at 0900.  This was followed by a long and very boring and hard to follow lecture by Jennifer Granick.  Jennifer is a lawyer, and the topic was the recent news about the NSA wiretapping, and what authorizations the President has for such matters, as well as the checks and balances within Congress and the Judicial system to prevent this kind of occurrance.</p>
<p class="body">The first talk I attended was by fyodor, "Advanced Network Reconnaissance with Nmap."  It was very informative, and discussed three different missions, and how one would accomplish each in turn.  Fyodor released his latest version of Nmap, specifically for Shmoocon, and announced that very soon Nmap 4.0 would be released.  Some new features are, parallel reverse dns lookup, as well as a setting to control the maximum times Nmap retries to send the packets, the version detection list now has 3,000 signatures, and the os detection list has 1684 fingerprints.  After this talk I attended "Hacking the Friendly Skies," by Simple Nomad.  This was very interesting, and covered how when bored in an airport or plane, one can attack the automatic ad-hoc networks produced by laptops without a connection.  This occurs with laptops using Microsoft Windows to control their wireless.  If the laptop doesn't find it's normal infrastructure connection, it begins broadcasting as an ad-hoc beacon.</p>
<p class="body">I attended some of the other talks as well, but many of the younger security professionals weren't nearly as engaging in their lectures.  Many were also hard to follow, and some just couldn't stay on topic.  Overall I will say Shmoocon 2006 was well worth the price.  I paid $75 back in August or September.  Many people outside of the lectures were discussing techniques and new tools utilizing hotspots throughout the conference.  There were also a lot of yuppies attending a conference in the same hotel.  They were there for some business thing.  Very lame.  There was a Shmoocon party on Saturday night at a very nice club in DC.  I will definitely be attending next year, hopefully with some other staff from the NSR.</p>
</body>
