<title>Windows Vista</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/vista.jpg</img>
<date>1/16/2006</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Windows Vista has long been anticipated, but not welcomed as enthusiastically as Microsoft would like. In the beginning, the name was the subject of many a joke, and most of us still wish marketing had thought up a better name. Vista is the future of Microsoft, though, and most of us will have to use it eventually. So here's what's good, and what's bad.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>The Good: </strong></p>
<p class="body">Vista is more than an operating system. Going along with the platform craze started by Intel, I'll call Vista a platform as well, for software. It forces users to upgrade to new standards, a new base to work with for software developers. Vista isn't that much more than XP with a pretty face, but by forcing people to conform to minimum system requirements, developers can expect a certain capability in systems. Systems that are unable to run Vista won't have to be considered, cutting some time and cost out of the development cycle. In that sense, forced upgrades are good for pushing technology forward.</p>
<p class="body">Vista has a lot of improvements, and many of them are about security, such as the Trusted Computing support. DRM will be coded into the OS, to the delight of Hollywood . There's also improved stability, seen in Windows Display Driver Module. WDDM attempts to fix some issues with video card drivers, which often cause BSODs. Vista will feature improved graphics, called the Aero Glass UI, a UI utilizing DirectX 9 for fancy effects. Users with lesser computers can run Aero or Classic UI modes, which use less graphics power than Aero Glass. Vista improves support for new technologies, such as SATA2, PCI Express, 64-bit processors, hybrid hard drives, and multi-core. Not everything listed will have much of a performance impact, but again, having a standard set of technologies will allow developers and system builders more breathing room.</p>
<p class="body"><strong>The Bad: </strong></p>
<p class="body">Vista is naturally exciting and wonderful, but all the improvements and new features are going to drain a lot of power out of a computer, especially with all the graphical effects enabled. Naturally, Microsoft had been recommending a “modern processor”, leading many of us to believe that the OS would require a hefty system. Recently, hardware vendors have released minimum specifications, allowing us to see exactly how hefty a system is necessary.</p>
<p class="body">Here's a quick rundown on the minimum specs: </p>
<ul class="body">
  <li>Processor: Celeron D series (starting at 2.26 GHz) or AMD Sempron series (starting at 1.67 GHz) </li>
  <li>Memory: 512 MB of DDR-RAM </li>
  <li>Graphics: Intel Graphics Media Accelerator 950, GeForce 5-series, Radeon 9500</li>
</ul>
<p align="center" class="body"><i><img src="nsr_images/_articles/vistacost/XFX-GeForce-FX-5200-256MB.jpg" alt="GeForce 5200"><br>A GeForce 5200, the least powerful nVidia card for Vista.</i></p>
<p class="body">One should note that these are only minimum specifications. Slower computers should run Vista fine, but not with the speed or graphics Microsoft wants. The best experience will come with dual core processors, graphics cards with 512MB of RAM, around 2 GB of DDR2 memory. Microsoft would also prefer if you had PCI Express and SATA2 hard drives. On the plus side, these minimum specifications don't look horrendous. My three year old computer has much better specs than the minimum, running an AthlonXP 2500+, 1.5 GB of DDR, and a GeForce 6800 GT. I'm not worried. But my computer is still missing a lot of technology, and I wonder if Vista will be unforgiving about that.</p>
<p class="body">Imagine a low end Vista user. They'll be running minimum specs, but they're looking at performance that's not so good. Here's why: The user won't be running a 64-bit, dual core processor. I haven't heard about any performance optimizations for 32-bit processors, but since 64-bit is the future, I would expect Microsoft to have spent much of their time there. Single threaded processors might also struggle more with an operating system built for multiprocessing. The user will also have just 512 MB of DDR-RAM. Vista will probably use half of this, leaving just 256 MB to run other programs. With today's programs, that's not much, and as of right now, FireFox is using upwards of 100 MB on my system. It's not horrendous, but the user will feel their computer is slow. Finally, the user will have a Graphics Media Accelerator 950 in their computer. The problem starts with the design of this processor. It's not fully DirectX 9 compliant, so it will have to offload some graphics operations to the main processor. Plus, being integrated, it will use precious system memory, making the system feel even more sluggish.</p>
<p class="body">Today, most manufactured computers with XP start with 256 MB of DDR-RAM, a Celeron based on the Pentium 500-series, and integrated graphics. These are cheap computers, granted, but they are extremely low power. Vista 's recommended minimum requirements are twice that of current low end computers, and even with the minimum specs, most users won't be able to see the full benefits of Vista . These minimum specs will also cost twice as much. Admittedly, it's not that much more, but from a different perspective, the price of a new computer is even further out of reach.</p>
<p class="body">Manufacturers and hardware makers have been long awaiting Vista. New Microsoft operating systems always mean new hardware upgrades and massive OEM purchasing. The major manufacturers won't be selling any more AGP and PATA based computers. Instead, they'll be stocking up on SATA2 and PCI Express and DDR2 parts for December, when Vista comes out. By that time, AMD's socket M2 processors will also be using DDR2, leading me to predict that prices will rise, at least in the volatile RAM market.</p>
<p class="body">Rising prices shouldn't be the only issue. Some Vista content will require hardware that is nonexistent. Vista won't allow High Definition video playback on monitors that don't support HDCP, an encryption technology to protect video content. Currently, no monitor supports HDCP, so users will have to wait and buy one, or they will be stuck watching lower definition content. Microsoft admits that this is a problem, but is telling consumers that they should be asking for HDCP capable monitors, not blaming Microsoft for forcing us to buy new monitors that aren't out yet. Nevertheless, I will still blame Microsoft and their DRM-happy partners.</p>
<p align="center" class="body"><i><img src="nsr_images/_articles/vistacost/theater_hdcp_1.jpg" alt="HDCP Schematic"><br>An Illustration of how HDCP works.</i></p>
<p class="body">At CES 2006, most people were fairly unenthusiastic about Vista . It's an improvement, bringing features Linux and OSX have had to Windows, but there are a lot of problems with it. It's costly, and it will force many people to purchase more than they expect, and there's a lot of code that will prevent consumers from doing what content providers don't want them to do. If you ask me, it's not worth it yet, but we'll have to get it sooner or later.</p>
<p class="body">Complete Vista requirements can be found at: <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/technet/windowsvista/evaluate/hardware/vistarpc.mspx%20">Microsoft</a></p>
<p class="body">Note: Please visit <a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/?article=28994">TheInquirer</a> for an explanation on why SATA2 does not exist. For this reason, when I mention SATA2 in this article, I mean SATA 3GB/s with NCQ.</p>
<br>
<p class="citetext">Images from:<br>
<a href="http://www.theprojectorpros.com/learn.php?s=learn&p=theater_hdcp" target="_blank">Theprojectorpros.com</a><br>
<a href="http://vitorazevedo.com/index.php?paged=1" target="_blank">Vitorazevedo.com</a><br>
<a href="http://www.techtree.com/techtree/jsp/article.jsp?article_id=50502&cat_id=537" target="_blank">Techtree.com</a></p>
</body>
