<title>Vista and DRM</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/vista.jpg</img>
<date>2/26/2007</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body>
<p class="body">It’s true that Windows Vista has a lot of problems. Looking at all the features that were dropped and how few new features there are, it’s amazing to see that this new” OS took five years to complete. Still, Vista is the future of Windows and it deserves a good look.</p>
<p class="body">The problem is that people aren’t looking. The latest <a href="http://www.forbes.com/security/2007/02/10/microsoft-vista-drm-tech-security-cz_bs_0212vista.html" target="_blank">Forbes</a> article claims that the ever-present DRM system in Vista will ruin everything, basing some of its information of an <a href="http://www.theinquirer.net/default.aspx?article=37091" target="_blank">Inquirer</a> editorial. It’s true that DRM is <a href="http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/pubs/vista_cost.html" target="_blank">pervasive</a> in Vista, requiring compatible drivers and hardware. But Vista will not add DRM to your non-DRM media. Vista cannot disrupt the way you view non-DRM media. Vista only applies its advanced locking mechanism to previously DRM’d content, such as HD-DVD and BD-DVD. It’s ludicrous to think that Vista would add DRM or limit consumers from viewing non-DRM home movies. And from the official <a href="http://windowsvistablog.com/blogs/windowsvista/archive/2007/01/20/windows-vista-content-protection-twenty-questions-and-answers.aspx" target="_blank">Vista</a> blog:</p>
<p class="body">"Windows Vista's content protection mechanisms are only used when required by the policy associated with the content being played." For Windows Vista experiences, if the content does not require a particular protection, then that protection mechanism is not used."</p>
<p class="body">From a business standpoint, locking out non-DRM files would be financially terrible, as it would prevent the adoption of Vista to amateur and professional videographers and editors. From a software standpoint, this is unfeasible. It is impossible to monitor all the open source video codecs and players that can run on Windows, and therefore it is impossible to prevent non-DRM software on Vista. Homemade Xvid movies will still run, provided the codecs are ported. And even DRM encryption schemes can be broken, as DVD Jon and other hackers have proven.</p>
<p class="body">Sometimes it is interesting to listen to rumors. Just don’t base your decisions on rumor alone. See Vista for yourself and decide if it’s worth it.</p>
</body>
