<title>Wi-Fi Ate Its Veggies Growing Up</title>
<author>Brad Glinka</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/noimageavail.jpg</img>
<date>11/7/2005</date>
<area>tech</area>
<body>
<p class="body">Everyone knows the old adage that a computer is out of date by the time you open the box and plug it in.  While this is true to computers no one expects someone to say the same about your home or office's wireless network.  Whether you're running an old wireless A or G, Linksys or Microsoft, Dsl or Cable internet; on the horizon is a new long range network standard.  That standard is WiMax.  WiMax has been around for several years now, in the design process, and pushed to the back of the table, but recently the big shots in the technology world, Intel namely, have started investing in this idea.  Unlike the standard of today, where a high powered wireless antenna and receiver might reach a mile, key word being might.  The developers haven't decided on a frequency, which is why this is taking so long, seeing as how the radio spectrum is so crowded with tv and other transmissions.  Some believe WiMax should run in the upper spectrum's of around 5.1gHz, which would give it a range of about 1 mile, still greater then any Starbucks  or McDonald's hot spot, but would only maybe be able to penetrate one building.  Where as others, myself included think the new standard should operate at around 700mHz.  At this lower wavelength, developers could reach a 30 mile range, and not only penetrate multiple buildings but possibly any natural terrain.  The uses of this are numerous, and with such a long range it could eliminate the use of dial-up internet in areas where running the cable or dsl infrastructure is too costly for the cable and phone companies.  It could also be used to blanket large cities and other areas with wireless internet, just as the cell phone companies have already done.  The only downside to this in comparison to the current standard is that transfer rates would drop significantly, but the ability to connect anywhere in the covered area more then makes up for this.  Although right now the cost of a WiMax card is upwards of $200, and the coverage is severely limited, unless you go to the University of Georgia or live in Athens Georgia, with companies like Intel backing it, it will take off in major cities within a few more years, and soon you'll be seeing clever commercials and reading ads about it in your area.</p>
<p class="citetext">Information taken from:<br>
Max-pc Magazine November 2004<br>
http://www.cnn.com/2005/TECH/10/17/wireless.wimax/index.html<br></p>
</body>
