<title>Windows Live Writer</title>
<author>George Liu</author>
<img>nsr_images/_articles/_smalls/windows.gif</img>
<date>2/26/2007</date>
<area>pc</area>
<body>
<p class="body">These days, a blog is created every second. People are only too happy to blog about anything and everything and entire businesses have sprung up around these happy people. LiveJournal, Blogspot, and Wordpress are just some of the most popular free blog hosts. Unfortunately, not many blog sites have software to interface with them. Personally, I find using desktop software much easier than opening a browser and navigating to a website. I don't want to navigate to twenty different sites and suffer the immense torrent of Javascript that runs the sites. Instead, I'd like to open a light program and get things done, then and there.</p>
<p class="body">That's where <a href="http://windowslivewriter.spaces.live.com/" target="_blank">Windows Live Writer</a> comes in. A Microsoft production, Windows Live Writer is one of the betas of the Windows Live initiative. It’s a nifty little tool that interfaces with the most popular blogs, allowing posting from the desktop. FireFox plugins have been developed for BlogThis or Flickr functionality as well. It comes with a decent spellchecker and WYSIWYG (What You See Is What You Get) editing. For those that need it, there are the typical hand-holding tools for inserting links and pictures. Drafts can be saved, reopened, and finally published. You can even use Live Writer to manage multiple blog accounts, switchable with the click of a button. This definitely makes it a handy tool, since I have at least two active blogs, not counting the many inactive accounts. And since it interfaces with multiple webhosts, it's terrific for easily adding content. </p>
<p class="body"><a href="javascript:nothing()" onclick="window_load('nsr_images/_articles/windows_live_writer/livewriter.jpg','738','718')"><img src="nsr_images/_articles/windows_live_writer/livewriter_sm.jpg" alt="Windows Live Writer" border="0"></a></p>
<p class="body">Live Writer will attempt to show you the look of your weblog by downloading the website template, but it's a far cry from truly publishing the entry. Published entries are saved as XML files on the computer, handy for backups. It can get cluttered, though, so keep that hard drive clean. There aren’t many other drawbacks, except for the massive promoting of Windows Live Spaces (the default account option), but that isn’t too terrible either.</p>
<p class="body">I highly recommend you try this tool out if you run multiple blogs. Even if you only run one blog, it's still pretty cool.</p>
</body>
